Support Vector MachinesDr. Ashish TendulkarMachine Learning PracticeIIT Madras2
In this week, we will study how to implement supportvector machines for classification tasks with sklearn.3
Support Vector Machines (SVM) are a set of supervisedlearning methods used for classification, regression and outliersdetection. Support Vector MachinesIn sklearn, we have three methods to implement SVM.SVCNuSVCLinearSVCSVM constructs a hyper-plane or set of hyper-planes in a highor infinite dimensional space, which can be used forclassification, regression or other tasks.These are similar methods but, acceptslightly different sets of parameters.Implementation is based on libsvm.Faster implementation of linear SVMclassification with only linear kernel.Implementation is based on liblinear.4
shape (n_samples, n_features) -Training dataArray : holding the trainingsamplesXArray : holding the classlabels (strings or integers)yshape (n_samples) -X = [[0, 0], [1, 1]]1y = [0,1]15
How to implement SVC (C-Support VectorClassification)?Step 1: Instantiate a SVC classifier estimator. from sklearn.svm import SVCSVC_classifier = SVC()12Step 2: Call fit method on SVC classifier object with training featurematrix and label vector as arguments.# Model training with feature matrix X_train and # label vector or matrix y_trainSVC_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train)1236
How to perform regularization in SVC classifier?C Regularization parameterSVC_classifier = SVC(C=1.0)1Default:float valuestrength of the regularization is inversely proportional to Cstrictly positivepenalty is a squared l2 penaltyNote:7
How to specify kernel type to be used in thealgorithm ?kernel 'rbf''poly'SVC_classifier = SVC(kernel = 'rbf')1Default:'linear'If kernel = poly , set degree (any integer value)If kernel = callable is given it is used to pre-compute thekernel matrix from data matrices'sigmoid''precomputed'8
How to set kernel coefficient for 'rbf', 'poly' and'sigmoid' kernels?gamma float value'auto'value of gamma = number of features X.Var()*1value of gamma = number of features1'scale'SVC_classifier = SVC(gamma = 'scale')1Default:If kernel = 'poly' or 'sigmoid' , set coef0 which is anindependent term in kernel function (any integer value)9
After the classifier is fit on the training data, there are few attributeswhich reveal the details of support vectors. from sklearn.svm import SVCSVC_classifier = SVC()clf = SVC_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train) #to view indices of the support vectorsclf.support_ #to view the support vectorsclf.support_vectors_ #to view the number of support vectors for each classclf.n_support_123456789101112How to view support vectors?10
How to implement NuSVC ( -Support VectorClassification)?nStep 1: Instantiate a NuSVC classifier estimator. from sklearn.svm import NuSVCNuSVC_classifier = NuSVC()12Step 2: Call fit method on NuSVC classifier object with training featurematrix and label vector as arguments.# Model training with feature matrix X_train and # label vector or matrix y_trainNuSVC_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train)12311
is an upper bound on the fraction of margin errors and anda lower bound of the fraction of support vectors.nWhat is the significance of in NuSVC?nValue of should n(0, 1]Default:n = 0.5Instead of C in SVC, is introduced in NuSVC to control thenumber of support vectors and margin errors.nOther parameters for NuSVC are same as that of SVC.12
How to implement LinearSVC (Linear SupportVector Classification)?Step 1: Instantiate a LinearSVC classifier estimator. from sklearn.svm import LinearSVCLinearSVC_classifier = LinearSVC()12Step 2: Call fit method on SVC classifier object with training featurematrix and label vector as arguments.# Model training with feature matrix X_train and # label vector or matrix y_trainLinearSVC_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train)12313
Advantages of LinearSVCIt has more flexibility in the choice of penalties and lossfunctions since it is implemented in terms of liblinear.Scales better to large numbers of samples.Supports both dense and sparse input.14
How to provide penalty in LinearSVC classifier?LinearSVC_classifier = Linear_SVC(penalty = 'l2')1Default:penalty - adds a L2 penalty terml2 - adds a L1 penalty terml1 - leads to coef_ vectors that are sparse.l115
How to choose loss functions in LinearSVCclassifier?LinearSVC_classifier = Linear_SVC(loss = 'squared_hinge')1Default:Combination not supported:penalty='l1' and loss='hinge' loss parameter'hinge' - standard SVM loss'squared_hinge' - square of the hinge loss16
Some parameters in LinearSVC classifierC dual fit_intercept Regularization parameterSelect the algorithm to either solve the dual or primaloptimization problem.When n_samples >n_features, prefer dual=False.To calculate the intercept for the model.17
How to perform multi-class classification using SVM?SVC and NuSVC implement the 'one-versus-one' approachfor multi-class classification.LinearSVC implements 'one-vs-the-rest' approach for multi-class classification.multi_class 'ovr''crammer_singer'decision_function_shape 'ovo''ovr'18
Advantages of SVMEffective in high dimensional spaces.Effective in cases where number of dimensions is greater thanthe number of samples.Uses a subset of training points in the decision function(called support vectors), so it is also memory efficient. Versatile: different Kernel Functions can be specified for thedecision function.Disadvantages of SVMSVMs do not directly provide probability estimates, these arecalculated using an expensive five-fold cross-validation.Avoid over-fitting in choosing Kernel functions if the number offeatures is much greater than the number of samples.19
