End to end Machine LearningProjectMachine Learning Practice Course2
Outline 1. Steps in ML projects 2. Illustration through practical set up3
Excellent wine company wants to develop ML model for predicting winequality on certain physiochemical characteristics in order to replaceexpensive quality sensor. Let's understand steps involved in addressing this problem. ML Project4
Steps in ML projects1. Look at the big picture.2. Get the data.3. Discover and visualize the data to gain insights.4. Prepare the data for Machine Learning algorithms.5. Select a model and train it.6. Fine-tune your model.7. Present your solution.8. Launch, monitor and maintain your system.5
A few words of wisdom ML is usually a small piece in a big project. e.g. wine qualityprediction is a small piece in setting up the manufacturingprocess. Typically 10-15% of time is spent on ML. A lot more time is spent on capturing and processing dataneeded for ML and taking decisions based on output of MLmodule. Needs strong collaboration with domain experts, productmanagers and eng-teams for successful execution. 6
Step 1: Look at the big picture1. Frame the problem2. Select a performance measure3. List and check the assumptions 1.1 Frame the problem What is input and output? What is the business objective? How does company expects to use andbenefit from the model? Useful in problem framing Algorithm and performance measure selection Overall effort estimation What is the current solution (if any)? Provides a useful baseline7
Design consideration in problem framingIs this a supervised, unsupervised or a RL problem?Is this a classification, regression or some other task?What is the nature of the output: single or multiple outputs?Does system need continuous learning or periodic updates?What would be the learning style: batch or online?8
1.2 Selection of performance measureRegressionMean Squared Error (MSE) orMean Absolute Error (MAE)ClassificationPrecisionRecallF1-scoreAccuracy9
1.3 Check the assumptionsList down various assumptions about the task.Review with domain experts and other teams that plan to consume ML output.Make sure all assumptions are reviewed and approved before coding!10
Step 2: Get the dataData spread across multiple tables, files or documents with access control.Obtain appropriate access controls and authorizations.Get familiarized with data by looking at schema and a few rows. (Familiarity withSQL would be useful here.)import pandas as pdimport matplotlib.pyplot as pltimport seaborn as snsimport numpy as np1234Load basic libraries11
Let's first access our data - in this case, we need to download it from the web.It's a good practice to create a function for downloading and extracting thedata.data_url = 'https://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/machine-learning-databases/wine-quality/winequality-red.csv'data = pd.read_csv(data_url, sep=';')12Now that the data is loaded, let's examine it.12
2.1 Check data samplesLet's look at a few data samples with head() method.data.head()113
2.2 FeaturesIt's a good idea to understand significance of each feature by consulting the experts.FeatureSignificanceFixed acidityMost acids involved with wine or fixed or nonvolatile (donot evaporate readily)Volitile acidityThe amount of acetic acid in wine, which at too high oflevels can lead to an unpleasant, vinegar tasteCitric acidFound in small quantities, citric acid can add 'freshness'and flavor to winesResidual sugarit's rare to find wines with less than 1 gram/liter and wineswith greater than 45 grams/liter are considered sweet.ChloridesThe amount of salt in the wine. AlcoholThe percentage of alcohol contents in the wine. (Credits:)https://www.kaggle.com/uciml/red-wine-quality-cortez-et-al-200914
feature_list = data.columns[:-1].valueslabel = [data.columns[-1]] print ('Feature list:', feature_list)print ('Label:', label)12345Feature list: ['fixed acidity' 'volatile acidity' 'citric acid' 'residual sugar' 'chlorides' 'free sulfur dioxide' 'total sulfur dioxide' 'density' 'pH' 'sulphates' 'alcohol'] Label: ['quality']15
2.3 Data statisticsLet's use info() method to getquick description of data.data.info()116
Total entries: 1599 (Tiny dataset byML standard)There are total 12 columns: 11features + 1 labelLabel column: qualityFeatures: [fixed acidity, volitileacidity, citric acid, residual sugar,cholrides, free sulphur dioxide,total sulphur dioxide, density, pH,sulphates, alcohol]All columns are numeric (float64) andlabel is an integer.2.3 Data statistics17
In order to understand nature of numeric attribites, we use describe() method.data.describe()1This one prints count and statistical properties - mean, standard deviations andquartiles.18
The wine quality can be between 0 and 10, but in this dataset, the quality valuesare between 3 and 8. Let's look at the distribution of examples by the wine quality.data['quality'].value_counts()1High quality value better quality of wine-You can see that there are lots of samples of average wines than good or the poorquality ones.Many examples with quality = 5 or 619
The information can be viewed through histogram plot.A Histogram gives the count of how many samples occurs within a specific range (bins).The x-axis denotes the range of values in a feature andThe y-axis denotes the frequency of samples with those specific values.sns.set()data.quality.hist()plt.xlabel('Wine Quality')plt.ylabel('Count')1234Note taller bars for quality 5 and 6 compared to the other qualities.20
In a similar manner, we can plot all numerical attributes with histogram plot for quickexamination.21
A few observations based on these plots:1. Features are at different scales.2. Features have different distributions -A few are tail heavy. e.g. residual sugar, free so2A few have multiple modes. e.g. volitile acidity, citric acidBefore any further exploration, it's a good idea to separate test set and do not look at itin order to have a clean evaluation set.22
2.4 Create test setWhen we look at the test set, we are likely to notice patterns in that and basedon that we may select certain models.This leads to biased estimation on test set, which may not generalize well inpractice. This is called data snooping bias.23
Let's write a function to split the data into training and test. Make sure to set the seed sothat we get the same test set in the next run.def split_train_test(data, test_ratio): # set the random seed. np.random.seed(42) # shuffle the dataset. shuffled_indices = np.random.permutation(len(data)) # calculate the size of the test set. test_set_size = int(len(data) * test_ratio) # split dataset to get training and test sets. test_indices = shuffled_indices[:test_set_size] train_indices = shuffled_indices[test_set_size:] return data.iloc[train_indices], data.iloc[test_indices]1234567891011121314train_set, test_set = split_train_test(data, 0.2)124
Scikit-Learn provides a few functions for creating test sets based on 1. Random sampling, which randomly selects % points in the test set. k2. Stratified sampling, which samples test examples such that they arerepresentative of overall distribution.25
Random samplingtrain_test_split() function performs random sampling withrandom_state parameter to set the random seed, which ensures that thesame examples are selected for test sets across runs.test_size parameter for specifying size of the test set.shuffle flag to specify if the data needs to be shuffled before splitting.Provision for processing multiple datasets with an identical number of rows andselecting the same indices from these datasets.Useful when labels are in different dataframe.from sklearn.model_selection import train_test_split126
We can read the documentation for this function by using the following line of code:?train_test_split1from sklearn.model_selection import train_test_split127
Let's perform random sampling on our dataset:train_set, test_set = train_test_split(data, test_size=0.2, random_state=42)128
Stratified samplingData distribution may not be uniform in real world data.Random sampling - by its nature - introduces biases in such data sets.Recall the label distribution in our dataset: It's not uniform!sns.set()data.quality.hist()plt.xlabel('Wine Quality')plt.ylabel('Count')1234Many examples of class 5 and 6 compared to the other classes.This causes a problem while random sampling. The test distribution may not matchwith the overall distribution.29
How do we sample in such cases?We divide the population into homogenous groups called strata.Data is sampled from each stratum so as to match it with the overall data distribution.Scikit-Learn provides a class StratifiedShuffleSplit that helps us in stratified sampling.from sklearn.model_selection import StratifiedShuffleSplitsplit = StratifiedShuffleSplit(n_splits=1, test_size=0.2, random_state=42)for train_index, test_index in split.split(data, data['quality']): strat_train_set = data.loc[train_index] strat_test_set = data.loc[test_index]12345Let's examine the test set distribution by the wine quality that was used for stratifiedsampling.strat_dist = strat_test_set['quality'].value_counts() / len(strat_test_set) 130
Now compare this with the overall distribution:overall_dist = data['quality'].value_counts() / len(data)1Let's look at them side-by-side:dist_comparison = pd.DataFrame({'overall': overall_dist, 'stratified': strat_dist})dist_comparison['diff(s-o)'] = dist_comparison['stratified'] - dist_comparison['ovedist_comparison['diff(s-o)_pct'] = 100*(dist_comparison['diff(s-o)']/dist_compariso12331
You can notice that there is a small difference in most strata.dist_comparison132
random_dist = test_set['quality'].value_counts() / len(test_set) random_dist12Let's contrast this with random sampling:33
Sampling bias comparison Compare the difference in distribution of stratified and uniform sampling:Stratified sampling gives us test distribution closer to the overall distribution than therandom sampling.dist_comparison.loc[:, ['diff(s-o)_pct', 'diff(r-o)_pct']]134
Step 3: Data visualizationPerformed on training set.In case of large training set -Sample examples to form exploration set.Enables to understand features and their relationship among themselves and withoutput label.In our case, we have a small training data and we use it all for data exploration. There isno need to create a separate exploration set.It's a good idea to create a copy of the training set so that we can freely manipulate itwithout worrying about any manipulation in the original set.exploration_set = strat_train_set.copy()135
Scatter VisualizationWith seaborn library:sns.scatterplot(x='fixed acidity', y='density', hue='quality', data=exploration_set)1236
With matplotlib:exploration_set.plot(kind='scatter', x='fixed acidity', y='density', alpha=0.5, c='quality', cmap=plt.get_cmap('jet'))1237
Relationship between featuresStandard correlation coefficient between features.Ranges between -1 to +1Correlation = +1: Strong positive correlation between featuresCorrelation = -1: Strong negative correlation between featuresCorrelation = 0: No linear correlation between featuresVisualization with heat mapOnly captures linear relationship between features.For non-linear relationship, use rank correlationLet's calculate correlations between our features.corr_matrix = exploration_set.corr()138
Let's check features that are correlated with the label, which is quality in our case.corr_matrix['quality']1Notice that quality has strong positivecorrelation with alcohol content [0.48] andstrong negative correlation with volitileacidity [-0.38].39
Let's visualize correlation matrix with heatmap:plt.figure(figsize=(14,7))sns.heatmap(corr_matrix, annot=True)1240
41
You can notice:The correlation coefficient on diagonal is +1.Darker colors represent negative correlations, whilefainter colors denote positive correlations. For examplecitric acid and fixed acidity have strong positivecorrelation.pH and fixed acidity have strong negativecorrelation.Another option to visualize the relationship between thefeature is with scatter matrix. 42
from pandas.plotting import scatter_matrixattribute_list = ['citric acid', 'pH', 'alcohol', 'sulphates', 'quality']scatter_matrix(exploration_set[attribute_list])123For convenience ofvisualization, we show it fora small number of attributes.43
Similar analysis can be carried out with combined features - features that arederived from the original features.44
Note of wisdom1. Visualization and data exploration do not have to be absolutely thorough.2. Objective is to get quick insight into features and its relationship with other featuresand labels.3. Exploration is an iterative process: Once we build model and obtain more insights,we can come back to this step.45
Step 4: Prepare data for ML algorithmWe often need to preprocess the data before using it for model building due to varietyof reasons:Typical steps in data preprocessing are as follows:It's a good practice to make a copy of the data and apply preprocessing on that copy.This ensures that in case something goes wrong, we will at least have original copy ofthe data intact.Due to errors in data capture, data may contain outliers or missing values.Different features may be at different scales.The current data distribution is not exactly amenable to learning.1. Separate features and labels.2. Handling missing values and outliers.3. Feature scaling to bring all features on the same scale.4. Applying certain transformations like log, square root on the features.46
4.1 Separate features and labels from the training set.# Copy all features leaving aside the label.wine_features = strat_train_set.drop('quality', axis=1) # Copy the label listwine_labels = strat_train_set['quality'].copy()1234547
4.2 Data cleaningLet's first check if there are any missing values in feature set: One way to find that out iscolumn-wise.wine_features.isna().sum() # counts the number of NaN in each column of wine_fe1In this dataset, we do not have any missing values.48
In case, we have non-zero numbers in any columns, we have a problem of missingvalues.These values are missing due to errors in recording or they do not exist.If they are not recorded:Use imputation technique to fill up the missing values.Drop the rows containing missing values.If they do not exists, it is better to keep it as NaN.Sklearn provides the following methods to drop rows containing missing values:dropna()drop()It provides SimpleImputer class for filling up missing values with. say, median value.49
from sklearn.impute import SimpleImputerimputer = SimpleImputer(strategy='median')12The strategy contains instructions as how to replace the missing values. In this case,we specify that the missing value should be replaced by the median value.imputer.fit(wine_features)1In case, the features contains non-numeric attributes, they need to be dropped beforecalling the fit method on imputer object.SimpleImputer(add_indicator=False, copy=True, fill_value=None, missing_values=nan, strategy='median', verbose=0)50
Let's check the statistics learnt by the imputer on the training set:imputer.statistics_1array([ 7.9 , 0.52 , 0.26 , 2.2 , 0.08 , 14. , 39. , 0.99675, 3.31 , 0.62 , 10.2 ])Note that these are median values for each feature. We can cross-check it by calculatingmedian on the feature set:wine_features.median()151
Finally we use the trained imputer to transform the training set such that the missingvalues are replaced by the medians:tr_features = imputer.transform(wine_features)1This returns a Numpy array and we can convert it to the dataframe if needed:tr_features.shape1(1279, 11)wine_features_tr = pd.DataFrame(tr_features, columns=wine_features.columns)152
4.3 Handling text and categorical attributes4.3.1 Converting categories to numbers:from sklearn.preprocessing import OrdinalEncoderordinal_encoder = OrdinalEncoder()12Call fit_transform() method on ordinal_encoder object to convert text to numbers.The list of categories can be obtained via categories_ instance variable.One issue with this representation is that the ML algorithm would assume that thetwo nearby values are closer than the distinct ones.53
4.3.2 Using one hot encodingHere we create one binary feature per category - the feature value is 1 when the categoryis present else it is 0.Only one feature is 1 (hot) and the rest are 0 (cold).The new features are referred to as dummy features.Scikit-Learn provides a OneHotEncoder class to convert categorical values into one-hotvectors.from sklearn.preprocessing import OneHotEncodercat_encoder = OneHotEncoder()12We need to call fit_transform() method on OneHotEncoder object.The output is a SciPy sparse matrix rather than NumPy array. This enables us to savespace when we have a huge number of categories.In case we want to convert it to dense representation, we can do so with toarray()method.The list of categories can be obtained via categories_ instance variable.54
As we observed that when the number of categories are very large, the one-hot encodingwould result in a very large number of features.This can be addressed with one of the following approaches:Replace with categorical numerical featuresConvert into low-dimensional learnable vectors called embeddings55
4.4 Feature ScalingMost ML algorithms do not perform well when input features are on very differentscales.Scaling of target label is generally not required.4.5.1 Min-max scaling or NormalizationWe subtract minimum value of a feature from the current value and divide it by thedifference between the minimum and the maximum value of that feature.Values are shifted and scaled so that they range between 0 and 1.Scikit-Learn provides MinMaxScalar transformer for this.One can specify hyperparameter feature_range to specify the range of the feature.56
4.5.2 StandardizationWe subtract mean value of each feature from the current value and divide it by thestandard deviation so that the resulting feature has a unit variance.While normalization bounds values between 0 and 1, standardization does not boundvalues to a specific range.Standardization is less affected by the outliers compared to the normalization.Scikit-Learn provides StandardScalar transformation for feature standardization.Note that all these transformers are learnt on the training data and then applied on thetraining and test data to tranform them.Never learn these transformers on the full dataset.57
Transformation PipelineScikit-Learn provides a Pipeline class to line up transformations in an intended order.Here is an example pipeline:from sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import StandardScalertransform_pipeline = Pipeline([ ('imputer', SimpleImputer(strategy='median')), ('std_scaler', StandardScaler()),])wine_features_tr = transform_pipeline.fit_transform(wine_features)123456Let's understand what is happening here:Pipeline has a sequence of transformations - missing value imputation followed bystandardization.Each step in the sequence is defined by name, estimator pair.Each name should be unique and should not contain __ (double underscore).58
from sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import StandardScalertransform_pipeline = Pipeline([ ('imputer', SimpleImputer(strategy='median')), ('std_scaler', StandardScaler()),])wine_features_tr = transform_pipeline.fit_transform(wine_features)123456The output of one step is passed on the next one in sequence until it reaches the laststep.Here the pipeline first performs imputation of missing values and its result is passed forstandardization.The pipeline exposes the same method as the final estimator.Here StandardScalar is the last estimator and since it is a transformer, we callfit_transform() method on the Pipeline object.59
How to transform mixed features?The real world data has both categorical as well as numerical features and we need toapply different transformations to them.Scikit-Learn introduced ColumnTransformer for this purpose.from sklearn.compose import ColumnTransformer1In our dataset, we do not have features of mixed types. All our features are numeric. 60
num_attribs = list(wine_features)cat_attribs = ['place_of_manufacturing']full_pipeline = ColumnTransformer([ ('num', num_pipeline, num_attribs), ('cat', OneHotEncoder(), cat_attribs), ])wine_features_tr = full_pipeline.fit_transform(wine_features)1234567For the illustration purpose, here is an example code snippet:Here we apply num_pipeline on numerical features and OneHotEncoder transformation onthe categorical features.The ColumnTransformer applies each transformation to the appropriate columns and thenconcatenates the outputs along the columns.Note that all transformers must return the same number of rows.The numeric transformers return dense matrix while the categorical ones return sparsematrix. The ColumnTransformer automatically determines the type of the output based onthe density of the resulting matrix.61
Step 5: Select and train ML modelIt's a good practice to build a quick baseline model on the preprocessed data and getan idea about model performance.from sklearn.linear_model import LinearRegression lin_reg = LinearRegression()lin_reg.fit(wine_features_tr, wine_labels)1234LinearRegression(copy_X=True, fit_intercept=True, n_jobs=None, normalize=False)62
Now that we have a working model of a regression, let's evaluate performance of themodel on training as well as test sets.For regression models, we use mean squared error as an evaluation measure.from sklearn.metrics import mean_squared_error quality_predictions = lin_reg.predict(wine_features_tr)mean_squared_error(wine_labels, quality_predictions)12340.420657106006027863
Let's evaluate performance on the test set.We need to first apply transformation on the test set and then apply the model predictionfunction.# copy all features leaving aside the label.wine_features_test = strat_test_set.drop('quality', axis=1) # copy the label listwine_labels_test = strat_test_set['quality'].copy() # apply transformationswine_features_test_tr = transform_pipeline.fit_transform(wine_features_test) # call predict function and calculate MSE.quality_test_predictions = lin_reg.predict(wine_features_test_tr)mean_squared_error(wine_labels_test, quality_test_predictions)1234567891011120.3975913087501516464
Let's visualize the error between the actual and predicted values.plt.scatter(wine_labels_test, quality_test_predictions)plt.plot(wine_labels_test, wine_labels_test, 'r-')plt.xlabel('Actual quality')plt.ylabel('Predicted quality')1234The model seem to be making errorson the best and poor quality wines.65
Let's try another model: DecisionTreeRegressor.from sklearn.tree import DecisionTreeRegressortree_reg = DecisionTreeRegressor()tree_reg.fit(wine_features_tr, wine_labels)123DecisionTreeRegressor(ccp_alpha=0.0, criterion='mse', max_depth=None, max_features=None, max_leaf_nodes=None, min_impurity_decrease=0.0, min_impurity_split=None, min_samples_leaf=1, min_samples_split=2, min_weight_fraction_leaf=0.0, presort='deprecated', random_state=None, splitter='best')Notice similarity between two code snippets.Linear regressionDecision Treeslin_reg.fit(wine_features_tr,wine_labels)tree_reg.fit(wine_features_tr,wine_labels)66
quality_predictions = tree_reg.predict(wine_features_tr)mean_squared_error(wine_labels, quality_predictions)120.0quality_test_predictions = tree_reg.predict(wine_features_test_tr)mean_squared_error(wine_labels_test, quality_test_predictions)120.58125Note that the training error is 0, while the test error is 0.58. This is an example of anoverfitted model.67
plt.scatter(wine_labels_test, quality_test_predictions)plt.plot(wine_labels_test, wine_labels_test, 'r-')plt.xlabel('Actual quality')plt.ylabel('Predicted quality')123468
We can use cross-validation (CV) for robust evaluation of model performance.from sklearn.model_selection import cross_val_score1Cross validation provides a separate MSE for each validation set, which we canuse to get a mean estimation of MSE as well as the standard deviation, whichhelps us to determine how precise is the estimate.The additional cost we pay in cross validation is additional training runs, whichmay be too expensive in certain cases.def display_scores(scores): print('Scores:', scores) print('Mean:', scores.mean()) print('Standard deviation:', scores.std())123469
Linear Regression CVscores = cross_val_score(lin_reg, wine_features_tr, wine_labels, scoring='neg_mean_squared_error', cv=10)lin_reg_mse_scores = -scoresdisplay_scores(lin_reg_mse_scores)1234Scores: [0.56364537 0.4429824 0.38302744 0.40166681 0.29687635 0.37322622 0.33184855 0.50182048 0.51661311 0.50468542] Mean: 0.431639217212196 Standard deviation: 0.0835635973041397670
Decision tree CVscores = cross_val_score(tree_reg, wine_features_tr, wine_labels, scoring='neg_mean_squared_error', cv=10)tree_mse_scores = -scoresdisplay_scores(tree_mse_scores)1234Scores: [0.6171875 0.6875 0.6328125 0.5078125 0.4609375 0.640625 0.65625 0.7109375 0.859375 1.07874016] Mean: 0.6852177657480315 Standard deviation: 0.16668343331737054Let's compare scores of Linear regression (LinReg) and decision tree(DT)regressions:LinReg has better MSE and more precise estimation compared to DT.71
Random forest CVRandom forest model builds multiple decision trees on randomly selected featuresand then average their predictions.Building a model on top of other model is called ensemble learning, which is oftenused to improve performance of ML models.from sklearn.ensemble import RandomForestRegressor forest_reg = RandomForestRegressor()forest_reg.fit(wine_features_tr, wine_labels) scores = cross_val_score(forest_reg, wine_features_tr, wine_labels, scoring='neg_mean_squared_error', cv=10)forest_mse_scores = -scoresdisplay_scores(forest_mse_scores)123456789Scores: [0.36989922 0.41363672 0.29063438 0.31722344 0.21798125 0.30233828 0.27124922 0.38747344 0.42379219 0.46229449] Mean: 0.34565226131889765 Standard deviation: 0.073632218430297372
quality_test_predictions = forest_reg.predict(wine_features_test_tr)mean_squared_error(wine_labels_test, quality_test_predictions)120.34449875plt.scatter(wine_labels_test, quality_test_predictions)plt.plot(wine_labels_test, wine_labels_test, 'r-')plt.xlabel('Actual quality')plt.ylabel('Predicted quality')1234Random forest looks more promising than the othertwo models.It's a good practice to build a few such modelsquickly without tuning their hyperparameters andshortlist a few promising models among them.Also save the models to the disk in Python pickleformat.73
What to do next?Model diagnosis RemedyUnderfitting Models with more capacityLessconstraints/regularizationOverfittingMore dataSimpler modelMoreconstraints/regularization74
Step 6: Finetune your modelUsually there are a number of hyperparameters in the model, which are setmanually.Tuning these hyperparameters lead to better accuracy of ML models.Finding the best combination of hyperparameters is a search problem in thespace of hyperparameters, which is huge.Grid searchScikit-Learn provives a class GridSearchCV that helps us in this pursuit.from sklearn.model_selection import GridSearchCV1We need to specify a list of hyperparameters along with the range of values to try.It automatically evaluates all possible combinations of hyperparameter values usingcross-validation.75
For example, there are number of hyperparameters in RandomForest regressionsuch as:Number of estimatorsMaximum number of featuresparam_grid = [ {'n_estimators': [3, 10, 30], 'max_features': [2, 4, 6, 8]}, {'bootstrap': [False], 'n_estimators': [3, 10], 'max_features': [2, 3, 4]},]1234Here the parameter grid contains two combinations:1. The first combination contains n_estimators with 3 values and max_features with4 values.2. The second combination has an additional bootstrap parameter, which is set toFalse. Note that it was set to its default value, which is True, in the first grid.76
Let's compute the total combinations evaluated here:Let's create an object of GridSearchCV:grid_search = GridSearchCV(forest_reg, param_grid, cv=5, scoring='neg_mean_squared_error', return_train_score=True)1231. The first one results in combinations.3 x 4 = 122. The second one has 2 values of n_estimators and 3 values of max_features, thusresulting in total of values.2 x 3 = 6The total number of combinations evaluated by the parameter grid 12 + 6 = 1877
Let's create an object of GridSearchCV:grid_search = GridSearchCV(forest_reg, param_grid, cv=5, scoring='neg_mean_squared_error', return_train_score=True)123In this case, we set cv=5 i.e. using 5 fold cross validation for training the model.We need to train the model for 18 parameter combinations and each combinationwould be trained 5 times as we are using cross-validation here.The total model training runs = 18 x 5 = 9078
Let's launch the hyperparameter search:grid_search.fit(wine_features_tr, wine_labels)179
The best parameter combination can be obtained as follows: grid_search.best_params_1{'max_features': 6, 'n_estimators': 30}Let's find out the error at different parameter settings:cvres = grid_search.cv_results_ for mean_score, params in zip(cvres['mean_test_score'], cvres['params']): print(-mean_score, params)80
cvres = grid_search.cv_results_ for mean_score, params in zip(cvres['mean_test_score'], cvres['params']): print(-mean_score, params)As you can notice the lowest MSE is obtained for the best parameter combination. 81
Let's obtain the best estimator as follows:grid_search.best_estimator_1Note: GridSearchCV is initialized with refit=True option, which retrains the bestestimator on the full training set. This is likely to lead us to a better model as it istrained on a larger dataset.82
Randomized SearchWhen we have a large hyperparameter space, it is desirable to tryRandomizedSearchCV.It selects a random value for each hyperparameter at the start of each iteration andrepeats the process for the given number of random combinations.It enables us to search hyperparameter space with appropriate budget control.from sklearn.model_selection import RandomizedSearchCV183
Analysis of best model and its errorsAnalysis of the model provides useful insights about features. let's obtain the featureimportance as learnt by the model: feature_importances = grid_search.best_estimator_.feature_importances_1sorted(zip(feature_importances, feature_list), reverse=True)1Based on this information, we may drop features that are not so important.It is also useful to analyze the errors in prediction and understand its causes and fixthem.84
Evaluation on test setNow that we have a reasonable model, we evaluate its performance on the test set. Thefollowing steps are involved in the process:# copy all features leaving aside the label.wine_features_test = strat_test_set.drop('quality', axis=1) # copy the label listwine_labels_test = strat_test_set['quality'].copy() # apply transformationswine_features_test_tr = transform_pipeline.fit_transform(wine_features_test)123456781. Transform the test features.85
2. Use the predict method with the trained model and the test set.quality_test_predictions = grid_search.best_estimator_.predict( wine_features_test_tr)123.Compare the predicted labels with the actual ones and report the evaluation metrics.mean_squared_error(wine_labels_test, quality_test_predictions)10.3534513888888888386
from scipy import statsconfidence = 0.95squared_errors = (quality_test_predictions - wine_labels_test) ** 2stats.t.interval(confidence, len(squared_errors) - 1, loc=squared_errors.mean(), scale=stats.sem(squared_errors))123456(0.29159276569581916, 0.4153100120819586)4.It's a good idea to get 95% confidence interval of the evaluation metric. It can beobtained by the following code:87
Step 7: Present your solutionOnce we have satisfactory model based on its performance on the test set, we reachthe prelaunch phase.Before launch,1. We need to present our solution that highlights learnings, assumptions andsystems limitation.2. Document everything, create clear visualizations and present the model.3. In case, the model does not work better than the experts, it may still be agood idea to launch it and free up bandwidths of human experts.88
Step 8: Launch, monitor and maintain your systemLaunchPlug in input sources andWrite test casesMonitoringSystem outagesDegradation of model performanceSampling predictions for human evaluationRegular assessment of data quality, which is critical for model performanceMaintenanceTrain model regularly every fixed interval with fresh data.Production roll out of the model.89
SummaryIn this module, we studied steps involved in end to end machine learning project withan example of prediction of wine quality.90
