Data PreprocessingMachine Learning PracticeDr. Ashish TendulkarIIT Madras1
The real world training data is usually not clean and has manyissues such as missing values for certain features, features ondifferent scales, non-numeric attributes etc. Often there is a need to pre-process the data to make itamenable for training the model.The same pre-processing should be applied to both trainingand test set. Sklearn provides pipeline for making it easier to chainmultiple transforms together and apply them uniformlyacross train, eval and test sets.Sklearn provides a rich set of transformers for this job.2
Once you get the training data, the first job is to explorethe data and list down preprocessing needed.Typical problems includeMissing values in featuresNumerical features are not on the same scale.Categorical attributes need to be representedwith sensible numerical representation.Too many features, reduce them.Extract features from non-numeric data.3
Sklearn provides a library of transformers fordata preprocessing. Data cleaning (sklearn.preprocessing) such asstandardization, missing value imputation, etc.Feature extraction (sklearn.feature_extraction)Feature reduction (sklearn.decomposition.pca)Feature expansion (sklearn.kernel_approximation)4
fit() method learns model parameters from a trainingset.Each transformer has the following methods:transform() method applies the learnt transformationto the new data.fit_transform() performs function of both fit() andtransform() methods and is more convenient andefficient to use.Transformer methods5
Part 1. Feature extraction6
FeatureHasherDictVectorizersklearn.feature_extraction has useful APIs to extractfeatures from data:Let's study these APIs one by one.7
DictVectorizerConverts lists of mappings of feature name and featurevalue, into a matrix.X='4x2413296.073.988.981.6Original dataTransformed featurematrix X'dv = DictVectorizer(sparse=False) dv.fit_transform(data)data = [{'age': 4, 'height':96.0},{'age': 1, 'height':73.9},{'age': 3, 'height':88.9},{'age': 2, 'height':81.6}]8
FeatureHasherHigh-speed, low-memory vectorizer that uses featurehashing technique.Instead of building a hash table of the features, as thevectorizers do, it applies a hash function to the featuresto determine their column index in sample matricesdirectly.This results in increased speed and reduced memoryusage, at the expense of inspectability; the hasher doesnot remember what the input features looked like andhas no inverse_transform method.Output of this transformer is scipy.sparse matrix.9
sklearn.feature_extraction.image.* has useful APIs to extractfeatures from image data. Find out more about them in sklearnuser guide at the following link: .Feature Extraction from ImagesFeature Extraction from images and textsklearn.feature_extraction.text.* has useful APIs to extractfeatures from text data. Find out more about them in sklearnuser guide at the following link: .Feature Extraction from Text10
Part 2: Data Cleaning11
Handling missing values12
Missing values occur due to errors in data capture such assensor malfunctioning, measurement errors etc.Discarding records containing missing values would resultin loss of valuable training samples.Many ML algorithms do not work with missing data and needall features to be present.sklearn.impute API provides functionality to fill missingvalues in a dataset.SimpleImputerKNNImputerprovides indicators for missing values.MissingIndicator13
SimpleImputerFills missing values with one of the following strategies:'mean', 'median', 'most_frequent' and 'constant'.X=4x27nan2918nan6 X='4x276291856Original featurematrix XTransformedfeature matrix X'si = SimpleImputer(strategy='mean') si.fit_transform(X)=37 + 2 + 96=31 + 8 + 6514
KNNImputerUses k-nearest neighbours approach to fill missingvalues in a dataset.The missing value of an attribute in a specificexample is filled with the mean value of the sameattribute of n_neighbors closest neighbors.The nearest neighbours are decided based onEuclidean distance.15
Example: KNNImputerConsider following feature matrix.X=4x31.3.nan8.2.4.6.8.nan3.5.7. It has 4 samples and 2 missing values.Let's fill in missing values with KNNImputer.16
dist(x, y) =weight x distance from present coordinates2Computing Euclidean distance in presence ofmissing valuesweight = number of present coordinatestotal number of coordinatesFor example, the distance between and is:x = [3, nan, nan, 6]y = [1, nan, 4, 5]dist(x, y) =2 x 53.3weight ==number of present coordinatestotal number of coordinates=242distance from present coordinates =2(3 -1) +2(6 -5) =2517
Let's fill the missing value in first sample/row.[3.4.3.][nan6.5.][8.8.7.]Distance with [1. 2.nan.]((1 -3) + (2 -4) )23223.46((1 -8) + (2 -8) )232211.29 nearestneighbours2[1. 2.4.]=23 + 54# of neighboursValues of the feature from nearest neighbours2X=4x31.3.nan8.2.4.6.8.nan3.5.7. (2 -6)1326.9218
X='4x41.3.5.58.2.4.6.8.4.3.5.7.X=4x41.3.nan8.2.4.6.8.nan.3.5.7. knni = KNNImputer(n_neighbors=2, weights='uniform') knni.fit_transform(X)Original featurematrix XTransformed featurematrix X'In this way, we can fill up the missing values with KNNImputer.19
Marking imputed valuesIt is useful to indicate the presence of missing values inthe dataset. helps us get those indications.It returns a binary matrix,True values correspond to missing entries inoriginal dataset.MissingIndicator20
1.2 Numeric transformers1. Feature scaling2. Polynomial transformation3. Discretization21
Let's learn how to scale numerical features with sklearnAPI.Feature scalingNumerical features with different scales leads to slowerconvergence of iterative optimization procedures.It is a good practice to scale numerical features so thatall of them are on the same scale.MaxAbsScalerMinMaxScalerStandardScalerThree feature scaling APIs are available in sklearn22
StandardScalerx ='sx -mTransforms the original features vector into new featurevector using following formulaxx'x=5x143256m = 4, s =2x='5x10-1/2-2/21/22/2 m ='0, s ='1ss = StandardScalar() ss.fit_transform(x)Note that the transformed feature vector hasmean ( ) = 0 and standard deviation ( ) = 1.x'msLearns parameters and .ms23
x ='x.max -x.minx -x.minIt transforms the original feature vector into new featurevector so that all values fall within range xx'[0, 1]where and are largest and smallest values ofthat feature respectively, of the original feature vector .x.maxx.minxMinMaxScalerx='5x110.350.50.60 x=5x11525-2-5mms = MinMaxScalar() mms.fit_transform(x) = 15, = -5 x.maxx.minThe largest number is transformed to 1 andthe smallest number is transformed to 0.24
x ='MaxAbsoluteValuexIt transforms the original features vector into new featurevector so that all values fall within range xx'[-1, 1]where MaxAbsoluteValue = max(x.max, |x.min|)MaxAbsScalerx='5x10.040.020.05-0.02-1 x=5x1425-2-100mas = MaxAbsScalar() mas.fit_transform(x) = MaxAbsoluteValuemax(5, |-100|) = 10025
Constructs transformed features by applying a user definedfunction.FunctionTransformerX='4x271291806X=4x2128245122256164 ft = FunctionTransformer(numpy.log2) ft.fit_transform(X)Applies function to the features.log226
Polynomial transformationGenerates a new feature matrix consisting of all polynomialcombinations of the features with degree less than or equalto the specified degree. X ='[x , x , x x , x , x ]12121222X ='[x , x , x x , x , x , x x , x x , x , x ]121212221221221323 X = [x , x ]12degree =2pf=PolynomialFeatures(degree=2) pf.fit_transform(X)pf=PolynomialFeatures(degree = 3) pf.fit_transform(X)degree =327
Divides a continuous variable into bins.One hot encoding or ordinal encoding is further appliedto the bin labels.x=9x100.1250.250.3750.50.6750.750.8751.0 KBinsDiscretizerx='9x10.0.1.1.2.3.3.4.4.KBinsDiscretizer( n_bins=5, strategy='uniform', encode = 'ordinal')28
1.2 Categorical transformers1. Feature encoding2. Label encoding29
OneHotEncoderEncodes categorical feature or label as a one-hotnumeric array.Creates one binary column for each of unique values.Exactly one column has 1 in it and rest have 0. Kx=4x11231X='4x3100101000010# unique values: K = 3ohe=OneHotEncoder() ohe.fit_transform(x)# columns intransformed matrix = 330
LabelEncoderEncodes target labels with value between 0 and , where is number of distinct values.K -1KHere : K = 4 {1, 2, 6, 8}y=6x1126186y='6x1012032le = LabelEncoder() le.fit_transform(y)1 is encoded as 0, 2 as 1, 6 as 2, and 8 as 3.31
OrdinalEncoderEncodes categorical features with value between 0 and , where is number of distinct values.K -1KOrdinalEncoder can operate multi dimensional data, whileLabelEncoder can transform only 1D data.X=6x2126186'male''female''female''male''male''female'X='6x2012032100110oe = OrdinalEncoder() oe.fit_transform(X)32
LabelBinarizery=6x1126186Y='6x4100100010000001001000010lb=LabelBinarizer() lb.fit_transform(y)Several regression and binary classification can be extendedto multi-class setup in one-vs-all fashion.This involves training a single regressor or classifier per class. For this, we need to convert multi-class labels to binary labels, and LabelBinarizer performs this task. If estimator supports multiclass data, LabelBinarizer is not needed.33
Encodes categorical features with value between 0 and , where is number of classes.K -1KMultiLabelBinarizermovie_genres =[{'action', 'comedy' },{'comedy'},{'action', 'thriller'},{'science-fiction', 'action', 'thriller'}]X='4x41011110000010011mlb = MultiLabelBinarizer() mlb.fit_transform(movie_genres)In this example , since there are only genres ofmovies.K = 4434
add_dummy_featureAugments dataset with a column vector, each value inthe column vector is .1X=4x271291806X='4x3111171291806add_dummy_feature(X)35
Part 2: Feature selectionFilter basedWrapper based36
Sometimes in a real world dataset, all features do notcontribute well enough towards fitting a model. The features that do not contribute significantly, can beremoved. It leads to decrease in size of the dataset andhence, the computation cost of fitting a model.sklearn.feature_selection provides many APIs toaccomplish this task.SelectFromModelVarianceThresholdGenericUnivariateSelectSequentialFeatureSelectorRFERFECVSelectKBestSelectPercentileNote: Tree based and kernel based feature selection algorithmswill be covered in later weeks.FilterWrapper37
Filter based feature selectionmethods38
Removing features with low varianceVarianceThresholdBy default removes a feature which has samevalue, i.e. zero variance.Removes all features with variance below acertain threshold, as specified by theuser, from input feature matrix 39
GenericUnivariateSelectUnivariate feature selectionUnivariate feature selection selects features based onunivariate statistical tests.SelectKBestSelectPercentileThere are three APIs for univariate feature selection:Removes all but thek highest scoringfeaturesRemoves all but a user-specified highest scoringpercentage of featuresPerforms univariate feature selection with aconfigurable strategy, which can be foundvia hyper-parameter search.40
sklearn provides one more class of univariate featureselection methods that work on common univariatestatistical tests for each feature:SelectFpr selects features based on a false positiverate test.SelectFdr selects features based on an estimatedfalse discovery rate.SelectFwe selects features based on family-wiseerror rate.41
Univariate scoring functionEach API need a scoring function to score each feature.Mutual information (MI)Chi-squareF-statisticsThree classes of scoring functions are proposed:MI and F-statistics can be used in both classification andregression problems.Chi-square can be used only in classification problems.mutual_info_regressionmutual_info_classiff_regressionf_classifchi242
Measures dependencybetween two variables.It returns a non-negativevalue.MI = 0 for independentvariables.Higher MI indicateshigher dependency. Mutual information (MI)Chi-squareMeasures dependencebetween two variables.Computes chi-square statsbetween non-negativefeature (boolean orfrequencies) and class label.Higher chi-square valuesindicates that the featuresand labels are likely to becorrelated.MI and chi-squared feature selection is recommended for sparsedata.43
SelectKBestskb = SelectKBest(chi2, k=20) X_new = skb.fit_transform(X, y)Selects 20 best features based on chi-square scoring function.sp = SelectPercentile(chi2, percentile=20) X_new = sp.fit_transform(X, y)ercentileSelectPSelects top 20 percentile best features based on chi-squarescoring function. GenericUnivariateSelecttransformer = GenericUnivariateSelect(chi2, mode='k_best', param=20) X_new = transformer.fit_transform(X, y)Selects 20 best features based on chi-square scoring function.'percentile' (default), 'k_best','fpr', 'fdr', 'fwe'44
GenericUnivariateSelectSelects set of features based on a feature selection modeand a scoring function.The mode could be 'percentile' (default), 'k_best', 'fpr','fdr', 'fwe'.The param argument takes value corresponding to the mode.transformer = GenericUnivariateSelect(chi2, mode='k_best', param=20) X_new = transformer.fit_transform(X, y)45
Do not use regression feature scoringfunction with a classification problem. It willlead to useless results.46
Wrapper based filter selectionUnlike filter based methods, wrapper basedmethods use estimator class rather than ascoring function.47
Recursive Feature Elimination ()RFEUses an estimator to recursively remove features.Initially fits an estimator on all features.Obtains feature importance from the estimator andremoves the least important feature.Repeats the process by removing features one byone, until desired number of features are obtained.Use if we do not want to specify the desirednumber of features in RFE .RFECVIt performs RFE in a cross-validation loop to find theoptimal number of features.48
SelectFromModelThe feature importance is obtained via coef_,feature_importances_ or an importance_getter callablefrom the trained estimatorSelects desired number of important features (as specifiedwith max_features parameter) above certain threshold offeature importance as obtained from the trained estimator.The feature importance threshold can be specified eithernumerically or through string argument based on built-inheuristics such as 'mean', 'median' and float multiples ofthese like '0.1*mean'.Let's look at a concrete example of SelectFromModel49
clf = LinearSVC(C=0.01, penalty='l1', dual=False) clf = clf.fit(X, y) clf.coef_ model = SelectFromModel(clf, prefit=True) X_new = model.transform(X)Here we use a linear support vector classifier to getcoefficients of features for SelectFromModel transformer. It ends up selecting features with non-zero weights orcoefficients.50
Sequential feature selectionPerforms feature selection by selecting or deselectingfeatures one by one in a greedy manner.Uses one of the two approachesForward selectionBackward selectionStarting with a zero feature, it findsone feature that obtains the bestcross validation score for an estimatorwhen trained on that feature.Repeats the process by adding a newfeature to the set of selected features.Stops when reach the desired number of features.Starting with all featuresand removes leastimportant features one byone following the idea offorward selection.51
The direction parameter controls whether forward or backwardSFS is used.In general, forward and backward selection do not yieldequivalent results.Select the direction that is efficient for the required number ofselected features:When we want to select 7 out of 10 features,Forward selection would need to perform 7 iterations.Backward selection would only need to perform 3.Backward selection seems to be a reasonable choice here.52
SFS does not require the underlying model to expose a coef_ orfeature_importances_ attributes unlike in RFE and SelectFromModel.SFS may be slower than RFE and SelectFromModel as it needs toevaluate more models compared to the other two approaches.For example in backward selection, the iteration going from features to features using -fold cross-validation requiresfitting models, whileRFE would require only a single fit, andSelectFromModel performs a single fit and requires noiterations.mm -1km x k53
Applying transformations todiverse features54
Generally training data contains diverse features suchas numeric and categorical.Different feature types are processed with differenttransformers.Need a way to combine different feature transformersseamlessly.55
sklearn.compose has useful classes and methods to applytransformation on subset of features and combine them:ColumnTransformerTransformedTargetRegressorComposite Transformer56
ColumnTransformerIt applies a set of transformers to columns of an array orpandas.DataFrame, concatenates the transformed outputs fromdifferent transformers into a single matrix.It is useful for transforming heterogenous data by applyingdifferent transformers to separate subsets of features.It combines different feature selection mechanisms andtransformation into a single transformer object.57
ColumnTransformer()Each tuple has format(estimatorName,estimator(...), columnIndices)column_trans = ColumnTransformer( [('ageScaler', CountVectorizer(), [0]]), ('genderEncoder', OneHotEncoder(dtype='int'), [1])], remainder='drop', verbose_feature_names_out=False)58
Illustration of Column TransformerX=6x220.011.215.613.018.616.4'male''female''female''male''male''female'Consider following feature matrix, which represent weight andgender of a class of students.Here, first column is numeric, however, second column iscategorical, therefore different transformers have to be appliedon them.59
In this example, lets apply MaxAbsScaler on the numericcolumn and OneHotEncoder on categorical column.X=6x220.011.215.613.018.616.4'male''female''female''male''male''female'X='6x31.0.560.780.650.930.820.1.1.0.0.1.1.0.0.1.1.0.column_trans = ColumnTransformer( [('ageScaler', MaxAbsScaler(), [0]]), ('genderEncoder', OneHotEncoder(dtype='int'), [1])], remainder='drop', verbose_feature_names_out=False) column_trans.fit_transform(X)60
TransformedTargetRegressorTransforming Target for RegressionTransforms the target variable y before fitting aregression model.The predicted values are mapped back to the originalspace via an inverse transform.TransformedTargetRegressor takes regressor andtransformer to be applied to the target variable asarguments.import numpy as np from sklearn.linear_model import LinearRegression from sklearn.compose import TransformedTargetRegressor tt = TransformedTargetRegressor(regressor=LinearRegression(), func=np.log, inverse_func=np.exp) X = np.arange(4).reshape(-1, 1) y = np.exp(2 * X).ravel() tt.fit(X, y)61
Part 3: Dimensionality reduction62
Another way to reduce the number of featureis through unsupervised dimensionalityreduction techniques.sklearn.decomposition module has a number of APIs for this task.We will focus on how to perform featurereduction with principle component analysis(PCA) in sklearn.63
PCA, is a linear dimensionality reduction technique.It uses singular value decomposition (SVD) to projectthe feature matrix or data to a lower dimensional space.The first principle component (PC) is in the direction ofmaximum variance in the data.It captures bulk of the variance in the data.The subsequent PCs are orthogonal to the first PC andgradually capture lesser and lesser variance in the data.We can select first PCs such that we are able tocapture the desired variance in the data.kPCA 101sklearn.decomposition.PCA API is used for performingPCA based dimensionality reduction.64
PCA illustrationBlue dots are data points. and are features., and are candidatePCs.x1x2C1 C2C3 represents projection ofdata points on a candidatevector.z65
Out of 3 candidate vectors toproject data on, vector capturesmost of the variance, hence it is thefirst PC and , which is orthogonalto it is the second PCC1C266
After applying PCA and choosing only first PC to reducedimension of data.67
Part 4: Chaining transformers68
The preprocessing transformations are applied one afteranother on the input feature matrix.It is important to apply exactly same transformation ontraining, evaluation and test set in the same order.Failing to do so would lead to incorrect predictions frommodel due to distribution shift and hence incorrectperformance evaluation.si = SimpleImputer() X_imputed = si.fit_transform(X) ss =StandardScaler() X_scaled = ss.fit_transform(X_imputed)69
ClassUsagePipelineConstructs a chain of multiple transformers toexecute a fixed sequence of steps in datapreprocessing and modelling.FeatureUnionCombines output from several transformerobjects by creating a new transformer fromthem.The module provides utilities to build acomposite estimator, as a chain of transformers andestimators.sklearn.pipelineThere are two classes: (i) Pipeline and (ii) FeatureUnion.70
sklearn.pipeline.PipelineSequentially apply a list of transformers and estimators.The purpose of the pipeline is to assemble severalsteps that can be cross-validated together whilesetting different parameters. Intermediate steps of the pipeline must be'transformers' that is, they must implement fit andtransform methods.The final estimator only needs to implement fit.71
Pipeline()Creating Pipelinesmake_pipelineIt takes a list of('estimatorName',estimator(...)) tuples.The pipeline object exposesinterface of the last step.It takes a number of estimatorobjects only.estimators = [ ('simpleImputer', SimpleImputer()), ('standardScaler', StandardScaler()), ] pipe = Pipeline(steps=estimators)pipe = make_pipeline(SimpleImputer(), StandardScaler())Two ways to create a pipeline object.72
estimators = [ ('simpleImputer', SimpleImputer()), ('standardScaler', StandardScaler()), ] pipe = Pipeline(steps=estimators) pipe.fit_transform(X)si = SimpleImputer() X_imputed = si.fit_transform(X) ss =StandardScaler() X_scaled = ss.fit_transform(X_imputed)Without pipeline:With pipeline:73
Accessing individual steps in Pipelineestimators = [ ('simpleImputer', SimpleImputer()), ('pca', PCA()), ('regressor', LinearRegression()) ] pipe = Pipeline(steps=estimators)The second estimator can beaccessed in following 4 ways:pipe.named_steps.pcapipe.steps[1]pipe[1]pipe['pca']Total # steps: 31. SimpleImputer2. PCA3. LinearRegression74
Accessing parameters of each step in PipelineParameters of the estimators in the pipeline can beaccessed using the <estimator>__<parameterName> syntax,note there are two underscores between <estimator> and<parameterName>estimators = [ ('simpleImputer', SimpleImputer()), ('pca', PCA()), ('regressor', LinearRegression()) ] pipe = Pipeline(steps=estimators) pipe.set_params(pca__n_components = 2)In above example n_components of PCA() step is set after thepipeline is created.75
Performing grid search with pipelineBy using naming convention of nested parameters, gridsearch can implemented.param_grid = dict(imputer=['passthrough', SimpleImputer(), KNNImputer()], clf=[SVC(), LogisticRegression()], clf__C=[0.1, 10, 100]) grid_search = GridSearchCV(pipe, param_grid=param_grid)C is an inverse of regularization, lower its value strongerthe regularization is.In the example above clf__C provides a set of values forgrid search.76
Caching transformersTransforming data is a computationally expensive step.For grid search, transformers need not be applied forevery parameter configuration. They can be applied onlyonce, and the transformed data can reused.This can be achieved by setting memory parameter of apipeline object.memory can take either location of a directory in stringformat or joblib.Memory object.estimators = [ ('simpleImputer', SimpleImputer()), ('pca', PCA(2)), ('regressor', LinearRegression()) ] pipe = Pipeline(steps=estimators, memory = '/path/to/cache/dir')77
Combines multiple steps of end to end ML into single objectsuch as missing value imputation, feature scaling andencoding, model training and cross validation.Enables joint grid search over parameters of all theestimators in the pipeline.Makes configuring and tuning end to end ML quick and easy.Offers convenience, as a developer has to call fit() andpredict() methods only on a Pipeline object (assuming laststep in the pipeline is an estimator).Reduces code duplication: With a Pipeline object, onedoesn't have to repeat code for preprocessing andtransforming the test data.Advantages of pipeline78
Concatenates results of multiple transformer objects.Applies a list of transformer objects in parallel, and theiroutputs are concatenated side-by-side into a larger matrix.FeatureUnion and Pipeline can be used to create complextransformers.sklearn.pipeline.FeatureUnion79
Combining Transformers and PipelinesFeatureUnion() accepts a list of tuples.Each tuple is of the format:('estimatorName',estimator(...))num_pipeline = Pipeline([('selector',ColumnTransformer([('select_first_4', 'passthrough', slice(0,4))])), ('imputer', SimpleImputer(strategy='median')), ('std_scaler', StandardScaler()), ]) cat_pipeline = ColumnTransformer([('label_binarizer', LabelBinarizer(),[4]), ]) full_pipeline = FeatureUnion(transformer_list= [('num_pipeline', num_pipeline), ('cat_pipeline', cat_pipeline),])80
Visualizing Composite Transformersfrom sklearn import set_config set_config(display='diagram') # displays HTML representation in a jupyter context full_pipeline It creates the following visualization81
That's it from data preprocessing.Only way to master is to practice it withexamples.Read more about these methods in anddocumentation of different classes.sklearnuser guide on data transformation82
