
Machine Learning Program Indian Institute of Technology, Madras Large-scale Machine Learning (Refer Slide Time: 0:10) Namaste! Welcome to the next video of Machine Learning Practice Course. In this video, we will study how to handle large-scale datasets in Sklearn. In this course, So, far, we were able to load entire data in memory, and we are able to train and make inferences on all the data at once. The large-scale datasets may not fit in memory. And we need to devise strategies to handle it in context of training and prediction use cases. Large-scale datasets is what you will encounter in many of the real life applications of this age. There is explosion of data that different companies are collecting from their customers from their processes, from manufacturing units, from different devices. And in order to train machine learning models on this large-scale data, we need special handling of the data, the feature generation process, and retraining process. Fortunately, sklearn has some functionality for handling large-scale datasets. And the topic of this video is to understand what kind of tools that are available to us in order to perform large- scale learning with sklearn. In this topic, we will discuss tools available in sklearn for large-scale learning. We will discuss overview of handling large-scale data, incremental preprocessing, and learning, basically fit versus partial _fit.
So far, we were using fit function for training the model. Now partial _fit will be our friend. When it comes to large-scale datasets. We will provide a short demonstration for combining preprocessing and incremental learning towards the end of this collab. (Refer Slide Time: 2:09) So, large-scale machine learning differs from traditional machine learning, in the sense that it involves processing large amount of data in terms of its size, or number of samples, features and classes. There are many exciting developments in efficient large-scale learning on many real world use cases in the last decade. Although scikit-learn is optimized for smaller data, it does offer a
decent set of feature preprocessing and learning algorithms, such as classification regression, and clustering for large-scale data. So, one way to check whether there is a support for large-scale dataset in a given estimator or any other preprocessing functions in a scalar, you should check whether that particular API has a partial _fit method. If there is a partial _fit method, there is a good chance that that API will support large-scale learning. So, sklearn handles large-scale data through partial _fit method, instead of using the Fit method. So, what is the central idea? The central idea is to process data in batches and update the model parameters for every batch. This way of learning is referred to as incremental or out-of-core learning. So, you can see here that we cannot fit the entire data in memory, and call the fit method. So, what we will do is we will load as much of data as we can in memory. And we will use partial _fit method for that. And what partial _fit method does is it loads a batch of data in memory and performs the parameter estimation, then it loads the next batch in memory and updates the parameters of the model and it keeps doing it until it processes the entire data. So, the incremental learning may be required in the following two scenarios. One is for large datasets or out of memory datasets, where it is not possible to load entire data into the RAM at once. So, one can load data in chunks and fit the machine learning model for each chunk of the data. And that is another use case for machine learning task where a new batch of data comes with time. So, retraining the model with previous and new batch of data is computationally expensive process. So, instead of returning the model with the entire dataset, one can employ an incremental learning approach where the model parameters are updated with a new batch of data. So, let us look at the incremental learning support in scikit learn.
(Refer Slide Time: 04:58) To perform incremental learning scikit learn implements partial _fit method that helps in training and out of memory dataset. So, in other words it has the ability to learn incrementally from the batches of instances. In this collab, we will see an example of how to read process and train on such a large dataset that cannot be loaded in memory entirely. The partial _fit method is expected to be called several times consecutively on different chunks of dataset so, as to implement out-of-core learning. This function has some performance overhead. So, it is recommended to call it on a considerable large batch of data to overcome the limitations of overhead. So, let us look at attributes of partial _fit method. So, partial _fit method takes feature matrix label vector, the list of classes and sample weights, as inputs list of classes and sample weights are optional. But, it is recommended that we supply the list of classes very first time when we call the partial _fit method that enables the partial _fit method to have the complete list of classes because since we are processing the data, chunk by chunk, it may happen that in the first chunk certain examples from certain classes might be missing.
(Refer Slide Time: 06:38) So, the following estimators in sklearn implement partial _fit method. As far as classification is concerned, Multinomial Naive Bayes, Bernoulli Naive Bayes, SGDClassifier and Perceptron implement partial _fit. And you know that with SGDClassifier we can implement different types of classifiers by changing the loss function. SGDRegressor also, implements partial _fit and it can be used for large-scale regression problems. And for clustering, this is a topic that we will be studying later in the course, there is a Mini BatchKMeans that also, implements partial _fit method. So, SGDRegressor, and SGDClassifier are commonly used for handling large datasets. Now, you may remember our discussion of gradient descent, batch gradient descent and stochastic gradient descent. So, any algorithm that uses let us say full batch gradient descent something like support vector machine random forest, of course, we have to discuss these algorithms they will be coming in subsequent weeks. So, one of the limitation is that because they are using full batch gradient descent, they need to load all the data in memory before performing any learning. And when we are working with large-scale dataset, loading all the data in memory is not an option because it is just not feasible. On the other hand SGD, if you remember Stochastic gradient descent updates the model parameter with a single example or even mini batch gradient descent uses a small number of examples to update the model parameters.
And the way SGDClassifier and regressors are implemented is that there is a facility to provide the number of examples as argument in SGDClassifier and regressor. So, SGD can deal with large datasets effectively by breaking up the data into chunks and processing them sequentially. So, for SGD we need to load only one chunk into memory at a time and SGD updates the model parameter with that chunk and it goes to the next chunk. So, this is very useful for handling large datasets and also, the data that comes in comes in intervals. (Refer Slide Time: 09:11)
So, for what we have studied is that there is a partial _fit method that helps us to handle the large datasets and possibly SGD is another powerful method at our disposal for handling large datasets. Let us look at a practical example of fit versus partial _fit. So, here what we do is we will be using a SGDClassifier for a classification problem on a synthetic dataset. And we will show the use of fit and partial _fit and show that both fit and partial _fit leads to similar kind of results. So, you first import the necessary libraries like SGDClassifier, then the dataset creation with make classification API. Then we also, import train _test _split in order to split the dataset into training and test. Then confusion matrix and classification report for evaluation of the model. So, what will
first do is we will use first fit but before that, we will generate a sample dataset that has got 50,000 samples with 10 features. And there are three classes. So, after generating the dataset, we split the data into training and test. So, which we set a size 15% examples for test. We make use of SGDClassifier with maximum number of iterations set to 1000 and tolerance set to 0.01. And you may recall that tolerance is used for deciding the convergence of the SGDClassifier will be using traditional fit method to train our model. So, here we simply called the fit method with the training feature matrix, and training labels, and we trained our SGDClassifier. So, we obtained the score of 0.87 on the training dataset. And on test data we also obtain very, very, very close test score. As with the training score, both the scores are 0.87. We look at the confusion matrix and classification report on the test set. And we obtained you can see that we obtained their first score of 0.90 for class 0 0.83 for class 1, and 0.88 for class 2. So, overall accuracy is 87%. Now what we will do is we will use partial _fit method instead of fit method. So, here, we generated a training data and use split method. And this is what we have been doing So, far in this course. Now the change would be that instead of fit, we will be using a partial _fit method. (Refer Slide Time: 12:26)

So, you may recall from our discussion, that partial _fit basically loads a small chunk of data in memory, processes them. And in processing, what it does is it actually trains the model on that chunk of data. Then it loads the next chunk and update the model parameters. So, this is how partial _fit method works. So, what we will do is, we will pretend that this dataset that we have generated, which has got 50,000 sample is we just cannot load the entire data in memory. So, what we will do is for that, we will load this data in chunks in memory, and then call the partial _fit method for training the model. So, let us see how to do that. So, we first concatenate the entire training feature metrics and training label into what is called as train data. And we store this train data into a CSV file. Now the data is in the file. And what we will do is we will read this file chunk by chunk and call the partial _fit method. So, we instantiate an SGDClassifier with maximum iteration, set to 1000 and tolerance set to 0.01. And this is where we are processing data chunk by chunk. So, we are going to use the read _csv function in pandas that has got attribute called chunksize. And the chunksize parameter specifies the number of rows per chunk that we want to that we want to read. So, here we set the chunk size 1000. So, we are going to read 1000 examples at a time and then call the partial _fit method on those 1000 examples. So, remember that while performing or while calling the partial _fit method for the first time, we need to also supply the list of classes that we have done here. That is why we
have a conditional statement here. So, if the iteration number is 1, then we call partial _fit with the list of classes. And for the subsequent iterations, we do not need to specify the list of classes and we simply specify the feature matrix and label vector. And after every iteration we are printing the coefficients and the intercepts that are obtained by the partial _fit method. So, here there are you can see that after every iteration we are printing the intercept. So, there are three classes. So, there are three intercepts, and there are three weight vectors one per each class. So, you can see that after every iteration the weight vector is kind of changing and also, the intercepts are changing. (Refer Slide Time: 15:38)
Now, after the training is complete we obtain the score on the test set it is 0.82 which is lower than what we obtained from the fit method earlier and f1-scores are also, slightly lower than what we obtained earlier we obtained f1-score on the class 0 the f1-score 0.88 for class 1 it is 0.77 and for class 2 it is 0.83 the overall accuracy is 82%. So, this was a small demonstration of how to use partial _fit method instead of the fit method. So, apart from SGDClassifier, we can also, train perceptron Multinomial Naive Bayes and Bernoulli Naive Bayes in a similar manner. (Refer Slide Time: 16:28)
So, far we have seen how to train a model in stepwise manner. Now, we will see how to perform preprocessing in stepwise or in incremental manner. So, here we show a couple of preprocessing techniques, which is CountVectorizer and HashingVectorizer. So, vectorizer used to convert a collection of text documents into a vector representation. So, this is a preprocessing step mainly in case of text data. So, CountVectorizer and HashingVectorizer both perform task of vectorizing the text document there is some differences between them. So, one difference is that HashingVectorizer does not have or does not store the resulting vocabulary. Hence, it is used to learn from the data that does not fit into the memory. So, each mini batch is vectorized using HashingVectorizer. So, as to guarantee that the input space of the estimator has always the same number of dimensions. With HashingVectorizer each token directly maps to a predefined column position in the matrix. So, for example, if there are 100 columns in the resultant matrix, each token would get mapped to one of the 100 columns, the mapping between the word and the position in the matrix is done using hashing. So, as the name suggests, it is HashingVectorizer. So, hashing, which is a technique that you must have studied in the data structure is used for generating a vector representation for the text data. (Refer Slide Time: 18:15) So, HashingVectorizer, what happens is each token gets transformed into a column position. And we do not really meant in a vocabulary. And not storing vocabulary is very useful while handling
large datasets, because we just cannot hold a huge token vocabulary comprising of millions of words into memory since the memory is limited. So, since HashingVectorizer does not store vocabulary, it does not take much space, unlike the CountVectorizer. So, it also, alleviates any dependency with function calls performed on the previous chunk of data while performing incremental learning. So, HashingVectorizer is kind of another friend of ours when processing large-scale text datasets. (Refer Slide Time: 19:06) So, now what we will do is we will take some sample text documents and vectorize them using both CountVectorizer and HashingVectorizer. So, that you get an idea of how both these vectorizer work. So, these are 4 small text snippets. And what we will be doing is we will be first using a CountVectorizer and CountVectorizer is a preprocessing technique. And it is part of sklearn.feature _extraction.text module. So, we instantiate a count vector a CountVectorizer and then called fit _transform method. Now remember that this is a preprocessing technique. And each processing API has fit _transform method implemented. So, we pass the list of text documents to the fit _transform method. And we obtain we obtained a transformed representations or the vector representation of the documents. So, you can see that the shape of the, the feature, the feature matrix is 466 . So, 4 is the number of text document and 66 is the size of vocabulary, there are 66 unique tokens in these 4 documents.
(Refer Slide Time: 20:25)
So, here, the vocabulary is present in the dictionary format, where the key of the dictionary is a token. And the value is the ID assigned to this particular token. So, 000 has the ID 0, 122 has ID of 1, 150 is has the ID of 2, and so, on. So, we have 66 such kind of tokens. And we will assign IDs from 0 to 65. And we can also, see that these tokens are in alphabetical order. So, let us see how the text documents are represented. So, this is our text documents for text documents, and we will see how they are represented with CountVectorizer. (Refer Slide Time: 21:17)

So, we have what is called as a sparse matrix representation. So, we do not we do not show or we do not store all the 65 dimensions for each tokens, because not all 65 tokens will be present in a document. So, we only store the index of the tokens or index of the words that are present in the document for example, document 1 has got word or token with index 54. We can check it out what is the 54 token it is the it is a word 'the'. So, this word 'the' has come three times we can go here and actually check whether 'the' has come three times there is one third here second 'the' here, and there is a third 'the' over here. So, indeed, 'the' has come three times in the first document. And hence, you can So, this is the count of the word 'the'. In the same way the word 62 the word ID 62, which is word 'well' has come once in the document. Which we can go back and check again. So, there is word 'well', that has come once in the first document. So, you can see that count over here and so, on. So, this is how the documents are represented this is a sparse matrix representation, where we only store the indices of words as part of this representation. Similarly, we have the representation for the second document, then for the third document, as well as for the first document. And so we are not actually showing the entire presentation, because this listing would be too big. So, only few words in the second documents are shown here.
(Refer Slide Time: 23:30) Now, let us use HashingVectorizer instead of CountVectorizer for vectorizing the documents. So, we here we import the HashingVectorizer from sklearn.feature _extraction.text module. So, we instantiate an object of HashingVectorizer class. There is an important parameter which is n _features that declares a number of features in the output feature matrix we set it to 50. Now remember that do not set too small or too large number over here. Too small number will cause hash collisions and which will pollute the representation. But, if you set this to a very large number, it will cause large number of feature dimensions for each text document. Now let us
perform HashingVectorizer with fit _transform method. So, we call fit _transform method on HashingVectorizer by supplying the text documents. Let us examine the shape of transform feature matrix. So, there are 4 documents and each document is represented with 50 values and this 50 is equal to the n _feature attribute that we had specified. So, this is a sample representation for first text document. So, for every text document, we get a score from the from the HashingVectorizer. So, overall HashingVectorizer is a good choice if we are falling short of memory and resources or we need to perform incremental learning. However, CountVectorizer is a good choice if we need to access the actual tokens. (Refer Slide Time: 25:29)
Now in the final section of the collab, what we will do is we will combine the preprocessing and fitting in incremental learning. So, here we will be using HashingVectorizer, along with SGDClassifier. So, now what we will do is we will work on a small text classification task, which is sentiment analysis or sentiment prediction. So for that, what we will do is we will represent each document with CountVectorizer. And then, we will be using a SGDClassifier to detect or to classify the sentiment in the text document. And we will perform both HashingVectorizer an SGDClassifier in incremental manner. So, here we download a dataset from UCI machine learning library. So, instead of downloading
unzipping and reading, we directly read the zip csv file for that we are using urllib.request.url open. And then we also, use BytesIO and TextIOWrapper class to get the data. So, there are two columns in the data, which is the review under sentiment. So, let us explore the dataset a bit. So, you can see that there is a sentence in the review, which is Good case Excellent value under sentiment is 1. Then the second statement is Great for the jawbone sentiment is 1 third one is Tied to charger for conversations lasting more and this sentence is not complete here right now. And the sentiment is 0. The mic is great, the sentiment is fine and so, on. So, there are in all 999 reviews, and 999 sentiment 1 sentiment per review. (Refer Slide Time: 27:46)

And the sentiment is either 0 or 1, 0 meaning the negative sentiment and 1 meaning the positive sentiment. Now, we split the data into training and test set, we have 799 examples in the training. Since the data is in the in the text form, we need to vectorize it. And in order to perform the vectorization in an incremental manner, we use HashingVectorizer. So, we instantiate an object of HashingVectorizer. And then, we create an instance of a SGDClassifier with L2 regularization. And here we are using hinge-loss. So, this way of using SGDClassifier with hinge-loss, we basically get the SVM, which is the technique that we are going to learn in the next week. Now what we will do is we will first perform the vectorization of the documents. So, here we have 799 samples, we can very well use the fit method. But since you are trying to demonstrate the partial _fit method or incremental learning, we will assume that we do not have sufficient memory to handle all 799 samples in one go. So, what we will do is we will first take 400 samples from the training data and perform partial _fit on those 400 samples. Alternatively, we can also, think that we only have 400 samples available at a time and you fit our classifier with these 400 samples. And then whenever more samples will be available, we will basically update our model. So, partial _fit is also, useful in such a scenario. Then we first perform the transformation on the text document using CountVectorizer And then we call the partial _fit on the on the transformed
representation. So, we perform the transform feature matrix and the labels along with the list of classes. So, while performing the evaluation, we first transform the test set using the same CountVectorizer and call the score method on the classifier object by supplying the transform test representation along with test labels. And we obtained the score of 0.70 on the test set. So, this is using first 400 examples. (Refer Slide Time: 30:45) Now, what we will do is we will use the remaining 399 examples and perform the second round of partial _fit. So, here, this is the second part of the training data, we transform our documents with HashingVectorizer and then perform the partial _fit with SGDClassifier. After training the data, we evaluate it on the test set. And now you can see that our test accuracy has gone up to 0.76. In this video, we discussed how to train machine learning models on large datasets. We mainly use technique of incremental learning to partial _fit method. Any estimator and transformer implementing partial _fit method can be used for large-scale learning. We demonstrated working of large-scale learning with sentiment classification example. Now you have tools for solving real world large-scale learning problems.
