Polynomial regression1
How is polynomial regression modeltrained?Step 1: Apply polynomial transformation on the feature matrix.Step 2: Learn linear regression model (via normal equation orSGD) on the transformed feature matrix.Implementation tips: Make use of pipeline construct forpolynomial transformation followed by linear regressionestimator.Step 2: Learn linear regression model (via normal equation orSGD) on the transformed feature matrix.2
Set up polynomial regression model with normal equationfrom sklearn.linear_model import LinearRegressionfrom sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import PolynomialFeatures # Two steps: # 1. Polynomial features of desired degree (here degree=2)# 2. Linear regressionpoly_model = Pipeline([ ('polynomial_transform', PolynomialFeatures(degree=2))), ('linear_regression', LinearRegression())]) # Train with feature matrix X_train and label vector y_trainpoly_model.fit(X_train, y_train)12345678910111213Set up polynomial regression model with SGDfrom sklearn.linear_model import SGDRegressorfrom sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import PolynomialFeatures poly_model = Pipeline([ ('polynomial_transform', PolynomialFeatures(degree=2))), ('sgd_regression', SGDRegressor())])poly_model.fit(X_train, y_train)12345678Notice that there is a single line code change in two code snippets.3
How to use only interaction features forpolynomial regression?from sklearn.preprocessing import PolynomialFeaturespoly_transform = PolynomialFeatures(degree=2, interaction_only=True)12 is transformed to .[x , x ]12[1, x , x , x x ]1212Note that are excluded.[x , x ]12224
Hyperparameter tuning (HPT)5
Hyper-parameters are parameters that are not directly learntwithin estimators.In sklearn, they are passed as arguments to the constructor ofthe estimator classes. How to recognize hyperparameters inany sklearn estimator?For example,degree in PolynomialFeatureslearning rate in SGDRegressor6
How to set these hyperparameters?Select hyperparameters that results in the best cross validationscores.Hyper parameter search consists ofan estimator (regressor or classifier);a parameter space;a method for searching or sampling candidates;a cross-validation scheme; anda score function.7
Two generic HPT approaches implemented in sklearn are:RandomizedSearchCV samples a given number of candidatevalues from a parameter space with a specified distribution.GridSearchCV exhaustively considers all parametercombinations for specified values.8
What are the differences between grid andrandomized search?Grid searchRandomized searchSpecifies exact values ofparameters in gridSpecifies distributions ofparameter values and values aresampled from those distributions.Computational budget can bechosen independent of number ofparameters and their possiblevalues.The budget is chosen in terms ofthe number of sampledcandidates or the number oftraining iterations. Specified inn_iter argument9
What data split is recommended for HPT?DataLabelsTraining DataTraining LabelsValidation DataValidation LabelsTest DataTest Labels10
What are the steps in HPT?DataLabelsTraining DataTraining LabelsValidation DataValidation LabelsTest DataTest LabelsSTEP 1: Divide training data into training, validation and test sets.11
STEP 2: For each combination of hyper-parameter values learn amodel with training set.Training DataTraining LabelsHyperparameterValuesHyperparameterValuesHyperparameterValuesLearningAlgorithmsModelModelModelThis step creates multiple models.This step can be be run in parallel by setting n_jobs = -1.Some parameter combinations may cause failure in fittingone or more folds of data. This may cause the search tofail. Set error_score = 0 (or np.NaN) to set score for theproblematic fold to 0 and complete the search. Tips12
STEP 3: Evaluate performance of each model with validation set andselect a model with the best evaluation score.ModelValidationFold LabelsValidationFold DataPredictionBestModelBestHyperparameterValuesModelValidationFold LabelsValidationFold DataPredictionModelValidationFold LabelsValidationFold DataPerformancePredictionPerformancePerformance13
ModelTraining DataTraining LabelsValidation DataValidation LabelsBestHyperparameter ValuesLearningAlgorithmSTEP 4: Retrain model with the best hyper-parameter settings ontraining and validation set combined.14
STEP 5: Evaluate the model performance on the test set.ModelTest LabelsTest DataPerformancePredictionNote that the test set was not used in hyper-parameter searchand model retraining .15
What are some of model specific HPT available forregression tasks?Some models can fit data for a range of values of someparameter almost as efficiently as fitting the estimator for asingle value of the parameter.This feature can be leveraged to perform more efficientcross-validation used for model selection of this parameter.linear_model.LassoCVlinear_model.RidgeCVlinear_model.ElasticNetCV16
How to determine degree of polynomial regressionwith grid search?from sklearn.model_selection import GridSearchCVfrom sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import POlynomialFeaturesfrom sklearn.linear_model import SGDRegressor param_grid = [ {'poly__degree': [2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9]} ] pipeline = Pipeline(steps=[('poly', PolynomialFeatures()), ('sgd', SGDRegressor())]) grid_search = GridSearchCV(pipeline, param_grid, cv=5, scoring='neg_mean_squared_error', return_train_score=True) grid_search.fit(x_train.reshape(-1, 1), y_train)123456789101112131415161717
Regularization18
How to perform ridge regularization with specificregularization rate?fit, score, predict work exactly like other linear regression estimatorsfrom sklearn.linear_model import Ridgeridge = Ridge(alpha=1e-3)12Step 1: Instantiate object of Ridge estimatorStep 2: Set parameter alpha to the required regularization rate.[Option #1][Option #2]from sklearn.linear_model import SGDRegressorsgd = SGDRegressor(alpha=1e-3, penalty='l2')12Step 1: Instantiate object of SGDRegressor estimatorStep 2: Set parameter alpha to the required regularization rateand penalty = l2.19
How to search the best regularization parameterfor ridge?Search for the best regularization rate with built-in crossvalidation in RidgeCV estimator.[Option #1]Use cross validation with Ridge or SVDRegressor to searchfor best regularization.[Option #2]Grid searchRandomized search20
from sklearn.linear_model import Ridgefrom sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import PolynomialFeatures poly_model = Pipeline([ ('polynomial_transform', PolynomialFeatures(degree=2))), ('ridge', Ridge(alpha=1e-3))])poly_model.fit(X_train, y_train)12345678How to perform ridge regularization in polynomialregression?Set up a pipeline of polynomial transformation followed by the ridge regressor.Instead of Ridge, we can use SGDRegressor, as shown on previousslide, to get equivalent formulation.21
How to perform lasso regularization with specificregularization rate?fit, score, predict work exactly like other linear regression estimatorsfrom sklearn.linear_model import Lassolasso = Lasso(alpha=1e-3)12Step 1: Instantiate object of Lasso estimatorStep 2: Set parameter alpha to the required regularization rate.[Option #1][Option #2]from sklearn.linear_model import SGDRegressorsgd = SGDRegressor(alpha=1e-3, penalty='l1')12Step 1: Instantiate object of SGDRegressor estimatorStep 2: Set parameter alpha to the required regularization rateand penalty = l1.22
How to search the best regularizationparameter for lasso regularization?Search for the best regularization rate with built-in crossvalidation in LassoCV estimator.[Option #1]Use cross validation with Lasso or SVDRegressor to searchfor best regularization.[Option #2]Grid searchRandomized search23
from sklearn.linear_model import Lassofrom sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import PolynomialFeatures poly_model = Pipeline([ ('polynomial_transform', PolynomialFeatures(degree=2))), ('lasso', Lasso(alpha=1e-3))])poly_model.fit(X_train, y_train)12345678How to perform lasso regularization in polynomialregression?Set up a pipeline of polynomial transformation followed by the lasso regressor.Instead of Lasso, we can use SGDRegressor to get equivalentformulation.24
from sklearn.linear_model import Lassofrom sklearn.pipeline import Pipelinefrom sklearn.preprocessing import PolynomialFeatures poly_model = Pipeline([ ('polynomial_transform', PolynomialFeatures(degree=2))), ('elasticnet', SGDRegressor(penalty='elasticnet', l1_ratio=0.3))])poly_model.fit(X_train, y_train)123456789How to perform both lasso and ridge regularizationin polynomial regression?Set up a pipeline of polynomial transformation followed by the SGDRegressor withRemember elasticnet is a convex combination of L1 (Lasso) and L2(Ridge) regularization.In this example, we have set l1_ratio to 0.3, which means l2_ratio= 1- l1_ratio = 0.7. L2 takes higher weightage in this formulation. penalty = 'elasticnet'25
SummaryHow to implementDifferent regression models: standard linear regression andpolynomial regression.Regularization.Model evaluation through different error metrics and scores derivedfrom them.Cross validation - different iteratorsHyperparameter tuning via grid search and randomized search.26
Appendix - MoreDetails27
IntroductionIn this module, we will be covering the implementation aspects ofmodels of linear regression.First we will learn linear regression models with:Normal equation, which estimates model parameter with aclosed-form solution. Iterative optimization approach of gradient descent and itsvariants namely batch, mini-batch and stochastic gradientdescent. 28
Since the polynomial regression uses moreparameters (due to polynomial representation of theinput), it is more prone to overfitting.We will study how to detect overfitting with learningcurves and use of regularization to mitigate the risk ofoverfitting.Further, we will study the implementation of the polynomialregression model, that is capable of modelling non-linearrelationships between features and labels.29
RecapLet's recall components of Linear regression30
Training Data(features, label) or , where label is a real number.(X, y)y31
Model = =y^w +0w x +11w x +22... + w xmmw xTwhere, is the predicted value. is a feature vector for a given example with features in total. -th feature: Weight or parameter vector includes bias term too: is -the model parameter associated with -the feature. is a model with parameter vector .y^X{x , x , ... , x }12mmixiw{w , w , w , ... , w }012mwiiihwwThe label is obtained by a linear combination (or weighted sum) of theinput features and a bias (or intercept) term. The model is given byhw32
Loss functionJ(w) =-y21i=1n(y^(i)(i))2J(w) =w x-y21i=1n(T(i)(i))2The model parameters are learnt such that the square of differencebetween the actual and the predicted values is minimized.w33
Optimization1. Normal equation2. Iterative optimization with gradient descent: full batch, mini-batch orstochastic.34
Evaluation measure1. Mean squared error2. Root mean squared error35
Implementing with sklearn36
Normal equationfrom sklearn.linear_model import LinearRegression1sklearn provides LinearRegression estimator for weightvector estimation via normal equationlin_reg = LinearRegression(normalize=True)lin_reg.fit(X_train, y_train)12It's a good practice to scale or normalize features. We canset normalize flag to True for normalizing the input features.By default, normalize is False.As like other estimator object, it implements fit method thattakes dataset as an input along with any otherhyperparameters and returns estimated weight vector.37
It also implements a couple of other methods:predict: Predicts label for a new examples based on thelearnt model.score: Returns of the linear regression model.R238
Coefficient of determination R2R =21 -(vu)where is the residual sum of squares and is calculated as uu = (Xw -y)T (Xw -y )and is the total sum of square. Let, , then iscalculated as v=y^meanXwn1 ()vv = (y -) (y -y^mean T)y^mean39
The best possible score is 1.0.The score can be negative (because the model can be arbitrarilyworse). A constant model that always predicts the expected value of ,disregarding the input features, would get a score of 0.0.yR =21 -(vu)40
41
The learnt weights can be obtained by accessing the following classvariables of LinearRegression estimator:The intercept weight can be obtained via intercept_ classvariable.w0The weights can be obtained via coef_ class variable.lin_reg.intercept_, lin_reg.coef_1Model inspection42
Computational ComplexityThe normal equation uses the following equation to obtain w = X XX y(T)-1TThis involves matrix inversion operation of feature matrix . XThe `LinearRegression`estimator uses SVD for this task and has thecomplexity of where is the number of features.O(m )2m43
This implies that if we double the number of features, the trainingcomputation grows roughly 4 times.As the number of features grows large, the approach of normalequation slows down significantly.These approaches are linear w.r.t. the number of trainingexamples as long as the training set fits in the memory.The inference process is linear w.r.t. both the number of examplesand number of features.44
Weight vector estimation via SGD SGD is a simple yet very efficient approach of learning weightvectors in linear regression problems especially in large scaleproblem settings.SGD offers provisions for tuning the optimization process. Howeveras a downside of this, we need to set a few hyperparameters.SGD is sensitive to feature scaling.45
In sklearn, an estimator SGDRegressor implements a plain stochasticgradient descent learning routine which supports different loss functionsand penalties to fit linear regression models.SGDRegressor is well suited for regression problems with a largenumber of training samples (> 10,000). For learning problems withsmall number of training examples, sklearn user guide recommendsRidge or Lasso.46
Key functionalities of SGDRegressorLoss function:Can be set via the loss parameter.SGDRegressor supports the following loss functions.loss= 'squared error': Ordinary least squares,loss = 'huber': Huber loss for robust regression47
RegularizationSGD supports the following penalties:Penalty = 'l2' : L2 norm penalty on coef_ . This is default setting. penalty = 'l1': L1 norm penalty on coef_. This leads to sparsesolutions. penalty = 'elasticnet': Convex combination of L2 and L1;`(1 - l1_ratio) * L2 + l1_ratio * L148
The learning rate can be either constant or gradually decaying. Thereare following options for learning rate schedule specification in SGD:eLearning rate For regression the default learning rate schedule is inverse scalinglearning_rate = 'invscaling'. The learning rate in -th iteration or timestep is calculated aste=(t)tpower_te0where, and power_t are hyperparameters chosen by the user. e01. invscaling49
2. ConstantFor a constant learning rate use learning_rate = 'constant' and use to specify the learning rate.e050
3. Adaptive For an adaptively decreasing learning rate, use learning_rate ='adaptive' and use to specify the starting learning rate.e0When the stopping criterion is reached, the learning rate is dividedby 5, and the training loop continues.The algorithm stops when the learning rate goes below .10-651
4. OptimalUsed as a default setting for classification problems. The learning rate for -th iteration is calculated as follows:et e=(t)a(t + t)01Here is a regularization rate. a is the time step (there are a total of n_samples*n_iter time steps)t is determined based on a heuristic proposed by Leon Bottou suchthat the expected initial updates are comparable with the expectedsize of the weights (this assuming that the norm of the trainingsamples is approx. 1).t052
Stoping creteriaSGDRegressor provides two stopping criteria to stop the algorithmwhen a given level of convergence is reached:1. With early_stopping = TrueThe input data is split into a training set and a validationset based on the validation_fraction parameter. The model is fitted on the training set, and the stoppingcriterion is based on the prediction score (using thescoring method) computed on the validation set.53
2. With early_stopping = FalseThe model is fitted on the entire input data and The stopping criterion is based on the objective functioncomputed on the training data.54
In both cases, the criterion is evaluated once by epoch, and thealgorithm stops when the criterion does not improven_iter_no_change times in a row.The improvement is evaluated with absolute tolerance tol.The algorithm stops in any case after a maximum number of iterationmax_iter55
SGDRegressor supports averaged SGD (ASGD). Averaging can beenabled by setting average = TrueASGD performs the same updates as the regular SGD, and setscoef_ attribute to the average value of the coefficients across allupdates.SGD sets coef_ attribute to the last value of the coefficients(i.e. the values of the last update)SGD variation: Average SGDThe same process is followed for the intercept_ attribute. When using ASGD the learning rate can be larger and even constant,leading to a speed up in training.56
Model inspectionWe obtain the weight vector from the trained model as follows:coef_ variable stores weights assigned to the features.intercept_, as name suggests, stores the intercept term.57
ComplexityThe major advantage of SGD is its efficiency, which is basically linear inthe number of training examples. Recent theoretical results, however, show that the runtime to get somedesired optimization accuracy does not increase as the training set sizeincreases.If is a matrix of size training has a cost of .where is the number of iterations (epochs) and is the averagenumber of non-zero attributes per sample.X(n, m)O(knp)kp58
Polynomial regression59
Polynomial regressionPolynomial regression = Polynomial transformation + Linear RegressionPolynomialFeatures transformer transforms an input data matrix into anew data matrix of a given degree.60
Example:from sklearn.preprocessing import PolynomialFeaturesimport numpy as npX = np.arange(6).reshape(3, 2)print ('Data matrix: ', X)poly = PolynomialFeatures(degree=2)print (' After transformation: ', poly.fit_transform(X))123456Data matrix: [[0 1] [2 3] [4 5]] After transformation: [[ 1. 0. 1. 0. 0. 1.] [ 1. 2. 3. 4. 6. 9.] [ 1. 4. 5. 16. 20. 25.]]12345678910Output:61
In the above example, the features of have been transformed from to , and can now be used within any linearmodel.X[x , x ]121, x , x , x , x x , x[12121222]In some cases it's not necessary to include higher powers of any singlefeature, but only the so-called interaction features that multiply togetheras most distinct features. These can be gotten from'PolynomialFeatures' with the setting interaction_only = True.In this case, the features of would be transformed from to .X[x , x ]121, x , x , x x[1212]62
Ridge regression63
Ridge regression minimizes penalized sum of squared error.L2Ridge regressionRidge Loss = Sum of squared error + regularization_rate * penaltyWe use 'Ridge' estimator for implementing ridge regression. It takesparameter 'alpha' which is the regularization rate.'RidgeCV' estimator implements ridge regression with crossvalidation for regularization rate. 64
RidgeCV parameters:1. alphas is the list of regularization rates to try. The regularization rate must be positive. Larger values indicate stronger regularization.2. cv determines the cross-validation splitting strategy.None, to use the efficient Leave-One-Out cross-validationinteger, to specify the number of folds.CV splitter specifies how to generate cross validation sets.An iterable yielding (train, test) splits as arrays of indices.65
In case of a binary or multiclass problems, for 'cv=None' or 'cv=5' (i.e.integer), 'StratifiedKFold' cross validation strategy is used. In othercases, 'KFold' cross validation strategy is used.66
Model inspection'RidgeCV' provides an additional output apart from usual outputs likecoef_ and intercept_:alphas provides the estimated regularization parameter.67
Lasso regression68
Lasso regressionLasso uses norm of weight vector as a penalty in linear regressionloss function.L1'sklearn' provides two implementations for learning weight vector inLasso.'Lasso' uses coordinated descent algorithm. 'LassoLars' uses least angle regression algorithm. It isadaption of forward stepwise feature selection for solvingLasso regression.69
