Classification functions in sci-kitlearnDr. Ashish TendulkarMachine Learning PracticeIIT Madras2
In this week, we will study sklearn functionality forimplementing classification algorithms.We will cover sklearn APIs forSpecific classification algorithms for least squareclassification, perceptron, and logistic regressionclassifier.with regularizationmulticlass, multilabel and multi-output settingVarious classification metrics.Cross validation and hyper parameter search forclassification works exactly like how it works inregression setting.However there are a couple of CV strategies that arespecific to classification3
Part I: sklearn API forclassification4
Logistic regressionPerceptronRidge classifier (for LSC)K-nearest neighbours(KNNs)Support vector machines(SVMs)Naive BayesThere are broadly two types of APIs basedon their functionality:SpecificGenericSGD classifierUses gradientdescent for optSpecialized solvers for optNeed to specify lossfunction5
All sklearn estimators for classification implement a fewcommon methods for model training, prediction andevaluation.6
Model trainingfit(X, y[, coef_init, intercept_init, ...])Predictionpredict(X)decision_function(X)predicts class label for samplespredicts confidence score forsamples.Evaluationscore(X, y[, sample_weight])Return the mean accuracy on the given test data andlabels.7
There a few common miscellaneous methods as follows:get_params([deep])gets parameter for this estimator. converts coefficient matrix to dense array format.set_params(**params)densify()sparsify()sets the parameters of this estimator.converts coefficient matrix to sparse format.8
Now let's study how to implement different classifierswith sklearn APIs.9
Let's start with implementation of least squareclassification (LSC) with RidgeClassifier API.10
is a classifier variant of the regressor.RidgeClassifierRidgeRidge classifiertreated as multi-output regressionpredicted class corresponds to the output with the highest valueclassifier first converts binary targets to {-1, 1} and then treats theproblem as a regression task, optimizing the objective of regressor:Binary classification:Multiclass classification:minimize a penalized residual sum of squaressklearn provides different solvers for this optimizationsklearn uses to denote regularization ratepredicted class corresponds to the sign of the regressor'sprediction||Xw -wminy||+22a||w||22a11
How to train a least square classifier?Step 1: Instantiate a classification estimator without passing anyarguments to it. This creates a ridge classifier object.from sklearn.linear_model import RidgeClassifierridge_classifier = RidgeClassifier()12Step 2: Call fit method on ridge classifier object with training featurematrix and label vector as arguments.Note: The model is fitted using X_train and y_train.# Model training with feature matrix X_train and # label vector or matrix y_trainridge_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train)12312
How to set regularization rate in RidgeClassifier?Set alpha to float value. The default value is 0.1.alpha should be positive.Larger alpha values specify stronger regularization.from sklearn.linear_model import RidgeClassifierridge_classifier = RidgeClassifier(alpha=0.001)1213
How to solve optimization problem in RidgeClassifier?Using one of the following solverssvd cholesky sparse_cg lsqr sag , saga uses a Singular Value Decomposition of the feature matrix tocompute the Ridge coefficients.lbfgs uses scipy.linalg.solve function to obtain the closed-formsolutionuses the conjugate gradient solver of scipy.sparse.linalg.cg .uses the dedicated regularized least-squares routinescipy.sparse.linalg.lsqr and it is fastest.uses a Stochastic Average Gradient descent iterative procedure'saga' is unbiased and more flexible version of 'sag'uses L-BFGS-B algorithm implemented inscipy.optimize.minimize .can be used only when coefficients are forced to be positive.14
Uses of solver in RidgeClassifierFor large scale data, use 'sparse_cg ' solver.When both n_samples and n_features are large, use 'sag ' or'saga' solvers.Note that fast convergence is only guaranteed on featureswith approximately the same scale.15
How to make RidgeClassifier select the solverautomatically?auto chooses the solver automatically based onthe type of dataridge_classifier = RidgeClassifier(solver=auto)1 if solver == 'auto': if return_intercept: # only sag supports fitting intercept directly solver = 'sag' elif not sparse.issparse(X): solver = 'cholesky' else: solver = 'sparse_cg'12345678Default choice for solver is auto .16
If data is already centered, set fit_intercept as false, so that nointercept will be used in calculations.Is intercept estimation necessary forRidgeClassifier?ridge_classifier = RidgeClassifier(fit_intercept=True)1Default:17
How to make predictions on new datasamples?Use predict method to predict class labels for samples# Predict labels for feature matrix X_testy_pred = ridge_classifier.predict(X_test)12Other classifiers also use the same predict method.Step 2: Call predict method on classifier object with feature matrixas an argument.Step 1: Arrange data for prediction in a feature matrix of shape(#samples, #features) or in sparse matrix format.18
RidgeClassifierCV implementsRidgeClassifier with built-in cross validation.19
Let's implement perceptron classifier withPerceptron API.20
It is a simple classification algorithm suitable for large-scalelearning.Perceptron classificationShares the same underlying implementation with SGDClassifier Perceptron uses SGD for training.Perceptron() SGDClassifier(loss='perceptron', eta0=1,learning_rate='constant', penalty=None) 21
How to implement perceptron classifier?Step 1: Instantiate a Perceptron estimator without passing anyarguments to it to create a classifier object.from sklearn.linear_model import Perceptronperceptron_classifier = Perceptron()12Step 2: Call fit method on perceptron estimator object with trainingfeature matrix and label vector as arguments.# Model training with feature matrix X_train and # label vector or matrix y_trainperceptron_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train)12322
Perceptron can be further customized with the followingparameters:penalty (default = 'l2')alpha (default = 0.0001)l1_ratio (default = 0.15)fit_intercept (default = True)max_iter (default = 1000)tol (default = 1e-3)eta0 (default = 1)early_stopping (default = False)validation_fraction (default = 0.1)n_iter_no_change (default = 5)23
Perceptron classifier can be trained in an iterativemanner with partial_fit methodPerceptron classifier can be initialized to the weights ofthe previous run by specifying warm_start = True in theconstructor.24
Let's implement logistic regression classifierwith LogisticRegression API.25
LogisticRegression APIImplements logistic regression classifier, which is also knownby a few different names like logit regression, maximum entropyclassifier (maxent) and log-linear classifier. This implementation can fitbinary classificationone-vs-rest (OVR)multinomial logistic regressionProvision for or elastic-net regularizationl, l12arg min regularization penalty +w,CC cross entropy loss 26
How to train a LogisticRegression classifier?Step 1: Instantiate a classifier estimator without passing anyarguments to it. This creates a logistic regression object.from sklearn.linear_model import LogisticRegressionlogit_classifier = LogisticRegression()12Step 2: Call fit method on logistic regression classifier object withtraining feature matrix and label vector as arguments# Model training with feature matrix X_train and # label vector or matrix y_trainlogit_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train)12327
Logistic regression uses specific algorithms for solving theoptimization problem in training. These algorithms areknown as solvers.The choice of the solver depends on the classificationproblem set up such as size of the dataset, number offeatures and labels.28
How to select solvers for Logistic Regressionclassifier?solver 'newton-cg ''lbfgs ''liblinear ''sag 'saga 'For small datasets, 'liblinear' is agood choice, whereas 'sag' and'saga ' are faster for large ones.For multiclass problems, only'newton-cg', 'sag', 'saga' and 'lbfgs 'handle multinomial loss.'liblinear ' is limited to one-versus-rest schemeslogit_classifier = LogisticRegression(solver='lbfgs')1For unscaled datasets, 'liblinear','lbfgs' and 'newton-cg ' are robust.By default, logistic regression uses lbfgs solver.29
How to add regularization in Logistic Regressionclassifier?Regularization is applied by default because it improves numericalstability. penalty - adds a L2 penalty terml2 - adds a L1 penalty terml1elasticnet - both L1 and L2penalty terms are addednone - no penalty is addedlogit_classifier = LogisticRegression(penalty='l2')1By default, it uses L2 penalty.30
Not all the solvers supports all the penalties.Select appropriate solver for the desired penalty. L2 penalty is supported by all solversL1 penalty is supported only by a few solvers.SolverPenalty'newton-cg '['l2', 'none']'lbfgs '['l2', 'none']'liblinear' ['l1', 'l2']'sag' ['l2', 'none']'saga '['elasticnet', 'l1', 'l2', 'none']31
How to control amount of regularization inlogistic regression?sklearn implementation uses parameter C, which isinverse of regularization rate to control regularization. arg min regularization penalty +w,CC cross entropy loss RecallC is specified in the constructor and must be positiveSmaller value leads to stronger regularization.Larger value leads to weaker regularization.32
LogisticRegression classifier has a class_weight parameterin its constructor.What purpose does it serve?Exercise: Read on this parameter.stack overflow discussionHandles class imbalanace with differential classweights.Mistakes in a class are penalized by the class weight.Higher value here would mean higher emphasis onthe class.This parameter is available in classifier estimators in sklearn.33
LogisticRegressionCV implements logistic regression with in builtcross validation support to find the best values of C and l1_ratioparameters according to the specified scoring attribute.34
These classifiers can also be implemented with ageneric SGDClassifier API by setting the lossparameter appropriately.35
Let's study SGDClassifier API.36
SGD is a simple yet very efficient approach to fitting linearclassifiers under convex loss functionsSGDClassifierThis API uses SGD as an optimization technique and can beapplied to build a variety of linear classifiers by adjusting theloss parameter.Easily scales up to large scale problems with more than training examples and features. It also works with sparsemachine learning problemsText classification and natural language processing105105It supports multi-class classification by combining multiplebinary classifiers in a 'one versus all' (OVA) scheme.37
We need to set loss parameter appropriately to build trainclassifier of our interest with SGDClassifierloss parameter'hinge' - (soft-margin) linear Support Vector Machine'modified_huber' - smoothed hinge loss bringstolerance to outliers as well as probability estimates'log' - logistic regression'squared_hinge' - like hinge but is quadraticallypenalized'perceptron' - linear loss used by the perceptronalgorithm'squared_error', 'huber', 'epsilon_insensitive', or'squared_epsilon_insensitive' - regression losses38
By default SGDClassifier uses hinge loss and hencetrains linear support vector machine classifier.39
SGDClassifier(loss='log') LogisticRegression(solver='sgd') SGDClassifier(loss='hinge') Linear Support vector machineAn instance of SGDClassifier might have an equivalent estimatorin the scikit-learn API.40
How does SGDClassifier work?SGDClassifier implements a plain stochastic gradient descentlearning routine.the gradient of the loss is estimated with one sample at a timeand the model is updated along the way with a decreasinglearning rate (or strength) schedule.Advantages:Efficiency.Ease of implementation Disadvantages:Requires a number ofhyperparameters.Sensitive to feature scaling. It is importantto permute (shuffle) the training data before fitting the model.to standardize the features.41
How to use SGDClassifier for training a classifer?Step 1: Instantiate a SGDClassifer estimator by setting appropriateloss parameter to define classifier of interest. By default it uses hingeloss, which is used for training linear support vector machine.from sklearn.linear_model import SGDClassifier SGD_classifier = SGDClassifier(loss='log')12Step 2: Call fit method on SGD classifier object with training featurematrix and label vector as arguments.# Model training with feature matrix X_train and # label vector or matrix y_trainSGD_classifier.fit(X_train, y_train)123Here we have used `log` loss that defines alogistic regression classifier.42
How to perform regularization in SGD classifier?penalty - adds a L2 penalty terml2 - adds a L1 penalty terml1elasticnet - Convex combination of L2 and L1(1 - l1_ratio) * L2 + l1_ratio * L1 SGD_classifier = SGDClassifier(penalty='l2')1(l1_ratio controls the convex combination of L1 and L2 penalty. default=0.15)Default:Constant that multiplies the regularization term.Has float values and default = 0.0001alpha 43
How to set maximum number of epochs for SGDClassifier?SGD_classifier = SGDClassifier(max_iter=100)1Default:max_iter = 1000 The maximum number of passes over the training data (aka epochs)is an integer that can be set by the max_iter parameter.44
Some common parameters between SGDClassifierand SGDRegressorlearning_rate Stopping criteriatoln_iter_no_changemax_iterearly_stoppingvalidation_fractionwarm_start 45'constant''optimal''invscaling''adaptive''True''False'average SGDClassifier also supportsaveraged SGD (ASGD)
SummaryWe learnt how to implement the following classifiers withsklearn APIs:Least square classification (RidgeClassifier)Perceptron (Perceptron)Logistic regression (LogisticRegression)Alternatively we can use SGDClassifier with appropriateloss setting for implementing these classifiers:loss = `log` for logistic regressionloss = `perceptron` for perceptronloss = `squared_error` for least square classificationClassification estimators implements a few commonmethods like fit, score, decision_function, and predict.46
These estimators can be readily used in multiclass setting.They support regularized loss function optimization.All classification estimators have ability to deal withclass imbalance through class_weight parameter inthe constructor.47
Part II: Multi-learning classificationset up48
Let's extend these classifiers to multi-learning (multi-class, multi-label & multi-output) settings.49
Basics of multiclass, multilabel andmultioutput classificationMulticlass classification has exactly one output label andthe total number of labels > 2.For more than one output, there are two types of classificationmodels:Multilabeltotal #labels = 2Multiclass multioutput total #labels > 2We will refer both these models as multi-label classificationmodels, where # of output labels > 1.Multiclass, multilabel, multioutput problems are referred to asmulti-learning problems.50
Multiclassclassification(sklearn.multiclass)OneVsOneClassifierOneVsRestClassifierOutputCodeClassifierMultilabelclassification(sklearn.multioutput)MultiOutputClassifierClassifierChainproblemtypesmeta-estimatorssklearn provides a bunch of meta-estimators, which extend thefunctionality of base estimators to support multi-learningproblems.The meta-estimators transform the multi-learning problem into aset of simpler problems and fit one estimator per problem.51
Many sklearn estimators have built-in support for multi-learning problems.Meta-estimators are not needed for such estimators,however meta-estimators can be used in case wewant to use these base estimators with strategiesbeyond the built-in ones.InherentlymulticlassMulticlass asOVOMulticlass asOVRMultilabel52
InherentlymulticlassMultilabelLogisticRegression (multi_class = 'multinomial')RidgeClassifierLogisticRegressionCV (multi_class = 'multinomial')RidgeClassifierCVMulticlass asOVRPerceptronLogisticRegression (multi_class = 'ovr')SGDClassifierLogisticRegressionCV (multi_class = 'ovr')RidgeClassifierRidgeClassifierCV53
First we will study multiclass APIs in sklearn.54
Multi-class classificationClassification task with more than two classes.Each example is labeled with exactly one classIn Iris dataset,There are three class labels: setosa, versicolor and virginica.Each example has exactly one label of the three availableclass labels.Thus, this is an instance of a multi-class classification.In MNIST digit recognition dataset,There are 10 class labels: 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.Each example has exactly one label of the 10 available classlabels.Thus, this is an instance of a multi-class classification.55
How to represent class labels in multi-classsetup?Use LabelBinarizer transformation to convert the classlabel to multi-class format.Each example is marked with a single label out of klabels. The shape of label vector is . (n, 1)The resulting label vector has shape of .(n, k)from sklearn.preprocessing import LabelBinarizery = np.array(['apple', 'pear', 'apple', 'orange'])y_dense = LabelBinarizer().fit_transform(y)123 [[1 0 0] [0 0 1] [1 0 0] [0 1 0]]56
Let's say, you are given labels as part of the training set, howdo we check if they are is suitable for multi-classclassification?Use type_of_target to determine the type of the label. from sklearn.utils.multiclass import type_of_targettype_of_target(y)12In case, is a vector with more than two discrete values,type_of_target returns multiclass.y57
type_of_target can determine different typesof multi-learning targets.58
target_type'multiclass''multiclass-multioutput''unknown'yarray-like but none of the above, such as a 3darray,sequence of sequences, or an array of non-sequence objects.contains more than two discrete valuesnot a sequence of sequences1d or a column vector2d array that contains more than two discretevaluesnot a sequence of sequencesdimensions are of size > 1'multilabel-indicator'label indicator matrixan array of two dimensions with at least twocolumns, and at most 2 unique values.59
Examples>>> type_of_target([1, 0, 2])'multiclass'>>> type_of_target([1.0, 0.0, 3.0])'multiclass'>>> type_of_target(['a', 'b', 'c'])'multiclass'123456>>> type_of_target(np.array([[1, 2], [3, 1]]))'multiclass-multioutput'12multiclassmulticlass-multioutputmultilabel-indicatortype_of_target(np.array([[0, 1], [1, 1]]))'multilabel-indicator'>>> type_of_target([[1, 2]])'multilabel-indicator'123460
Apart from these, there are three more types, type_of_targetcan determine targets corresponding to regression andbinary classification.continuous - regression targetcontinuous-multioutput - multi-output targetbinary - classification61
All classifiers in scikit-learn perform multiclassclassification out-of-the-box.Use module only when you want toexperiment with different multiclass strategies.sklearn.multiclassUsing different multi-class strategy than the oneimplemented by default may affect performance ofclassifier in terms of either generalization error orcomputational resource requirement.62
What are different multi-class classificationstrategies implemented in sklearn?One-vs-all or one-vs-rest (OVR)One-vs-One (OVA)OVR is implemented by OneVsRestClassifier API.OVA is implemented by OneVsOneClassifier API.63
OVR - OneVsRestClassifierFits one classifier per class - .This approach is computationally efficient and requiresonly classifiers. The resulting model is interpretable.cc vs not ckOneVsRest classifier also supports multilabel classification. We need to supply labels as indicator matrix of shape .(n, k)from sklearn.multiclass import OneVsRestClassifierOneVsRestClassifier(LinearSVC(random_state=0)).fit(X, y)12We need to supply estimator as an argument in theconstructor.Support methods like other classifiers - fit, predict,predict_proba, partial_fit.64
OVA - OneVsOneClassifierFits one classifier per pair of classes. Total classifiers = .Predicts class that receives maximum votes.The tie among classes is broken by selecting the classwith the highest aggregate classification confidence. (2k)OneVsOne classifier processes subset of data at a time andis useful in cases where the classifier does not scale withthe data.from sklearn.multiclass import OneVsOneClassifierOneVsOneClassifier(LinearSVC(random_state=0)).fit(X, y)12We need to supply estimator as an argument in theconstructor.Support methods like other classifiers - fit, predict,predict_proba, partial_fit.65
What is the difference between OVR and OVA?OneVsRestClassifierOneVsOneClassifierFits one classifier per class.For each classifier, the class isfitted against all the otherclasses.Fits one classifier per pair ofclasses.At prediction time, the classwhich received the most votesis selected.66
Now we will learn how to perform multilabeland multi-output classification.67
How MultiOutputClassifier works?Input FeatureMatrix (X)Classifier #1Classifier #2Classifier #kClass #1Class #2Class #kStrategy consists of fitting one classifier per target.Allows multiple target variable classifications.68
How ClassifierChain works?A multi-label model that arranges binary classifiers into a chain.Way of combining a number of binary classifiers into a singlemulti-label model.69
Comparison of MultiOutputClassifier andClassifierChainMultiOutputClassifierClassifierChainAllows multiple target variableclassifications.Able to estimate a series oftarget functions that are trainedon a single predictor matrix topredict a series of responses.For a multi-label classificationproblem with classes, binaryclassifiers are assigned aninteger between 0 and .These integers define the orderof models in the chain.kkk -1Capable of exploitingcorrelations among targets.70
SummaryDifferent types of multi-learning setups: multi-class,multi-label, multi-output.type_of_target to determine the nature of suppliedlabels.Meta-estimators:multi-class: One-vs-rest, one-vs-onemulti-label: Classifier chain and multi-output classifier71
Evaluating Classifiers72
So far we learnt how to train classifiers for binary, multi-classand multi-label/output cases. We will learn how to evaluate these classifiers with differentscoring functions and with cross-validation.We will also study how to set hyper-parameters for classifiers. Many cross-validation and HPT methods discussed in theregression context are also applicable in classifiers.We will not repeat that discussion in this topic.Instead we will focus on only additional methods that arespecific to classifiers.73
There may be issues like class imbalance in classification,which tend to impact the cross validation folds. The overall class distribution and the ones in folds may bedifferent and this has implications in effective model training.sklearn.model_selection module provides three stratifiedAPIs to create folds such that the overall class distribution isreplicated in individual folds.Stratified cross validation iterators74
sklearn.model_selection module provides the followingthree stratified APIs to create folds such that the overallclass distribution is replicated in individual folds.StratifiedKFoldRepeatedStratifiedKFoldStratifiedShuffleSplitNote: Folds obtained via StratifiedShuffleSplit may not becompletely different.75
LogisticRegressionCVSupport in-build cross validation for optimizing hyperparametersThe following are key parameters for HPT and cross validationcv specifiescross validationiteratorscoring specifiesscoring function touse for HPTcs specifiesregularizationstrengths toexperiment with.Choosing the best hyper-parametersrefit = Truerefit = FalseScores averaged across folds, valuescorresponding to the best score are selectedand final refit with these parameters the coefs, intercepts and C that correspondto the best scores across folds are averaged.76
Now let's look at classification metricsimplemented in sklearn.77
sklearn.metrics implements a bunch of classification scoringmetrics based on true labels and predicted labels as inputs.accuracy_scorebalanced_accuracy_scoretop_k_accuracy_scoreroc_auc_scoreprecision_scorerecall_scoref1_scorescore(actual_labels, predicted_labels)Classification metrics78
Confusion matrixconfusion_matrix evaluates classification accuracy by computingthe confusion matrix with each row corresponding to the true class.from sklearn.metrics import confusion_matrixconfusion_matrix(y_true, y_predicted)12Entry in a confusion matrixi, jExample:number of observations actually in group ,but predicted to be in group .ij79
Confusion matrix can be displayed with ConfusionMatrixDisplayAPI in sklearn.metrics.Confusion matrixFrom estimatorsFrom predictionsConfusionMatrixDisplay(confusion_matrix=cm, display_labels=clf.classes_)1ConfusionMatrixDisplay.from_estimator(clf, X_test, y_test)1ConfusionMatrixDisplay.from_predictions(y_test, y_pred)180
The classification_report function builds a text report showingthe main classification metrics.from sklearn.metrics import classification_reportprint(classification_report(y_true, y_predicted))1281
Classifier Performance across probabilitythresholdsfrom sklearn.metrics import precision_recall_curveprecision, recall, thresholds = precision_recall_curve(y_true, y_predicted)12from sklearn.metrics import roc_curvefpr, tpr, thresholds = metrics.roc_curve(y_true, y_scores, pos_label=2)1282
How to extend binary metric to multiclass ormultilabel problems?Treat data as a collection of binary problems, one for each class.Then, average binary metric calculations across the set of classes.Can be done using average parameter.calculates the mean of the binary metricscomputes the average of binary metrics in which each class'sscore is weighted by its presence in the true data sample.gives each sample-class pair an equal contribution to theoverall metriccalculates the metric over the true and predicted classes foreach sample in the evaluation data, and returns their averagereturns an array with the score for each classmacro weighted micro samples None 83
SummaryClassification specific cross validation iterator based onstratification.Classification metricsExtending binary metrics to multi-learning set up.84
