Decision treesDr. Ashish TendulkarIIT MadrasMachine Learning Practice2
Non-parametric supervised learning methods.Can learn classification and regression models.Predicts label based on rules inferred from thefeatures in the training set.Quick recap 3
Tree algorithms4
sklearn implementation of treesscikit-learn uses an optimized version of the CARTalgorithm; however, it does not support categoricalvariables for nowsklearn.tree.DecisionTreeRegressorsklearn.tree.DecisionTreeClassifierClassificationRegressionBoth these estimators have the same set of parametersexcept for used for tree splitting.criterionsplittermax_depthmin_samples_splitmin_samples_leaf5
sklearn tree parametersThe minimum number of samples requiredto be at a leaf node.splittermax_depthmin_samples_splitmin_samples_leafbestrandomStrategy for splitting at each node. intintintfloatfloat2The minimum number of samples requiredto split an internal node.1Maximum depth of the tree.When , the tree expanded until all leaves arepure or they contain less than samples. Nonemin_samples_split6
sklearn tree parameterscriterionSpecifies function to measure the qualityof a split. ClassificationRegressionginientropysquarred_errorfriedman_mseabsolute_errorpoisson7
Tree visualizationsklearn.tree.plot_treeThe decision tree to be plotted.Names of each of the features.The maximum depth of the representation. If , the tree is fully generated.noneNames of each of the target classes inascending numerical order.Whether to show informative labels for impurity.decision_treemax_depthfeature_namesclass_nameslabelnonenonenone8
Avoiding overfitting of treesPre-pruningPost-pruningUses hyper-parameter search like forfinding the best set of parameters.GridSearchCVFirst grows trees without any constraints and then uses with and .cost_complexity_pruningmax_depthmin_samples_split9
Tips for practical usageDecision trees tend to overfit data with a large number offeatures. Make sure that we have the right ratio of samplesto number of features.Perform dimensionality reduction (PCA, or FeatureSelection) on a data before using it for training the trees.It gives a better chance of finding discriminative features.Visualize the trained tree by using max_depth=3 as aninitial tree depth to get a feel for the fitment and thenincrease the depth.Balance the dataset before training to prevent the treefrom being biased toward the classes that are dominant.10
Use min_samples_split or min_samples_leaf to ensurethat multiple samples influence every decision in the tree,by controlling which splits will be considered.A very small number will usually mean the tree willoverfit.A large number will prevent the tree from learning thedata.11
